<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A preparative to an hue and cry after Sir Arthur Haslerig, (a late Member of the forcibly dissolved House of Commons, and now the present wicked, bloody, and tyrannicall governor of Newcastle upon Tine) for his severall ways attempting to murder, and by base plots, conspiracies and false witnesse to take away the life of Lieutenant Colonel John Lilburn now prisoner in the Tower of London: as also for his felonious robbing the said Lieut Col. John Lilburn of betwixt 24 and 2500 l. by the meer power of his own will, ... In which action alone, he the said Haslerig hath outstript the Earl of Strafford, in traiterously subverting the fundamentall liberties of England, ... and better and more justly deserves to die therefore, then ever the Earl of Strafford did ... by which tyrannicall actions the said Haslerig is become a polecat, a fox, and a wolf, ... and may and ought to be knockt on the head therefore, ... / All which the said Lieutenant Col. John Lilburn hath cleerly and evidently evinced in his following epistle of the 18 of August 1649, to his uncle George Lilburn Esquire of Sunderland, in the county of Durham.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88237</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E573_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12119</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859216</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859216</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111285</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88237)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111285)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 88:E573[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A preparative to an hue and cry after Sir Arthur Haslerig, (a late Member of the forcibly dissolved House of Commons, and now the present wicked, bloody, and tyrannicall governor of Newcastle upon Tine) for his severall ways attempting to murder, and by base plots, conspiracies and false witnesse to take away the life of Lieutenant Colonel John Lilburn now prisoner in the Tower of London: as also for his felonious robbing the said Lieut Col. John Lilburn of betwixt 24 and 2500 l. by the meer power of his own will, ... In which action alone, he the said Haslerig hath outstript the Earl of Strafford, in traiterously subverting the fundamentall liberties of England, ... and better and more justly deserves to die therefore, then ever the Earl of Strafford did ... by which tyrannicall actions the said Haslerig is become a polecat, a fox, and a wolf, ... and may and ought to be knockt on the head therefore, ... / All which the said Lieutenant Col. John Lilburn hath cleerly and evidently evinced in his following epistle of the 18 of August 1649, to his uncle George Lilburn Esquire of Sunderland, in the county of Durham.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Dated and signed at end: 18 of Aug. 1649. .. John Lilburn.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septemb: 13 1649".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hesilrige, Arthur, --  Sir, d. 1661 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Detention of persons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111285:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A PREPARATIVE TO AN HUE AND CRY AFTER Sir ARTHUR HASLERIG, <hi>(A late Member of the FORCIBLY DISSOLVED Houſe of Commons, and now the preſent wicked, bloody, and tyrannicall Governor of Newcaſtle upon Tine)</hi>
            </head>
            <p>For his ſeverall ways attempting to MURDER, and by <hi>baſe plots, conſpiracies and falſe Witneſſe</hi> to take away the life of Lieutenant Colonel <hi>JOHN LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN</hi> now <hi>Priſoner</hi> in the <hi>Tower</hi> of London: As alſo for his <hi>felonious Rob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing</hi> the ſaid Lieut Col. <hi>JOHN LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN</hi> of betwixt 24 and 2500 <abbr>l.</abbr> by the <hi>meer</hi> power of his <hi>own will,</hi> without ever fixing any <hi>reall</hi> or pretended <hi>crime</hi> upon the ſaid <hi>Lieutenant Col.</hi> or ſo much as affording him any <hi>formall</hi> proceedings, <hi>though upon a paper Petition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN WHICH ACTION ALONE, he the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>HASLERIG</hi> hath outſtript the Earl of <hi>STRAFFORD, in traiterouſly ſulverting</hi> the fundamentall <hi>Liberties of England,</hi> and (in time of Peace) exerciſing <hi>an arbitrary and tyrannicall Government,</hi> OVER AND ABOVE LAW, and better and more juſtly deſerves to die therefore, then ever the Earl of STRAFFORD did (eſpecially, conſidering he <hi>was one</hi> of his Judges, that for ſuch actions condemned him to <hi>loſe his head as a Traytor</hi>) by which <hi>tyrannicall actions</hi> the ſaid HASLERIG is become a <hi>Polecat,</hi> a <hi>Fox,</hi> and a <hi>Wolf,</hi> (as a ſubverter and deſtroyer of humane ſociety) <hi>and may and ought to be knockt on the head therefore,</hi> by the very words of Solicitor St. JOHN's own doctrine againſt the ſaid Earl of <hi>Strafford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which the ſaid Lieutenant Col. JOHN LILBURN hath cleerly and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently evinced <hi>in his following Epiſtle of the</hi> 18 <hi>of Auguſt</hi> 1649, to his Uncle GEORGE LILBURN ESQUIRE OF SUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERLAND, in the County of <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Iſa. 1.14.</hi>
                     </bibl> Your new Moons, and your appointed Feaſts my ſoul hateth: they are a trouble to me, I am weary to bear them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 15.</hi>
                     </bibl> And when you ſpread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you; yea, when you make many prayers, I will not hear: your hands are full of blood.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOurs of the 2 preſent from Durham, about Sir <hi>Arthur Hoſlerig</hi> and <hi>my Money,</hi> I have received: In anſwer unto which, I cannot chuſe but acquaint you, that the Law of England <q>is the Birth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght and Inheritance of the people of England, yea, of the meaneſt as well as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> richeſt: 1 Part Parliaments Book of Declarat. pag. 459. 660.</q> And though the Law of England be not ſo good, and ſo exact in every particular, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:111285:2"/>
manifeſtly proved; Firſt, that before indictment the goods or other things of any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor cannot be ſearched, inventoried, or in any ſort ſeiſed, nor after judgement ſeiſed and removed, or taken away before conviction or Attainder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">Secondly, That the begging of the goods or ſtate of any delinquent, accuſed or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of any Treaſon, felony, or any other offence, before he be convicted and attainted, is utterly unlawfull; becauſe before conviction or attainder, as hath been ſaid, nothing is forfeited to the King, nor grantable by him; and beſides it either makes the proſecution againſt the delinquent more precipitate, violent, and undue, then the quiet and equall proceeding of law and juſtice would<note n="(*)" place="margin">See notably to this purpoſe in the <hi>2</hi> p. inſtit. fol. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> permit, or elſe by ſome underhand compoſition and agreement, ſtop and hinder the due courſe of juſtice, for exemplary puniſhment of the offender; And laſtly, when the Delinquent is beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, it diſcourageth, both Judge, Juror and Witneſſe to do their duty. Therefore (ſaith he there) let ſuch as beg the delinquent, and proſecute againſt him be terrified by the villanous judgment againſt conſpirators, which you may read before, cap. 1. Judgment and execution, fol. 122. as alſo fol. 143 163, 164. and 1 par. fol. 269. and 2 par. fol. 130. 237, 238. 562. which are moſt excellent peeces, and well worth the reading.</hi> Therefore conſidering what is before expreſſed, I cannnot but wonder upon what<note n="(*)" place="margin">Peruſe carefully I intreat you the quotations in the <hi>6</hi> and <hi>8</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of my forementioned impeachment of high Treaſon againſt <hi>Cromwel,</hi> as alſo the <hi>12</hi> and <hi>15</hi> pages of the <hi>2</hi> edition of my fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Book, dated the <hi>8</hi> of June <hi>1649.</hi> Intituled The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall fundamentall liberties, &amp;c.</note> pretence Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> Col. <hi>George Fenwick,</hi> and the reſt of their Committee at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle,</hi> can ſeize upon my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in the hands of Sir <hi>Henry Belli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gham,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Thomas Bowes,</hi> and ſtopping my rents du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom Sir <hi>Henry Gibs</hi> his hands, to the full value of betwixt twenty four and twenty five hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>For firſt, though the late Parliament in the height of wars, a little outſtript the bounds and rules of the law, as themſelves confeſſe in their notabl. Declaration of the 17 of Apr. 1646. printed in the 2 part of the Book of Declarations, pag. 879 in ſequeſtring of mens eſtates, in another manner and forme the law requires delinquents eſtates to be ſeiſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe their perſons by reaſon of the raging of the ſword could not be come by, nor were all the Courts of Juſtice open, nor the wants of the common-wealth to maintaine the wars, could not well permit ſo great delays, as the regular courſe of the law requires, which when the wars are over (as in England now they are) they promiſe to amend and <hi rend="margQuotes">to proceed according to the forme of the law, as fully appeares in their laſt foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Declaration, add ſeverall others, as particularly the Declaration of this preſent Juncto againſt Kingſhip, Dated the 17 of March 1648.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I am ſure by the Parliaments own Ordinances, <q>no man in times of wars ought to be ſequeſtred, till it be judicially upon Oath proved, that he hath been in arms againſt them, all voluntarily contributed horſe, mony or plate to the King againſt them;</q> none of all which in the leaſt can be ſo much as be pretended againſt me, or ever was; and therefore no cauſe to pretend to deal with me, as with a <hi>Cavalier Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent</hi> in the leaſt; and therefore if I have tranſgreſſed, I muſt upon their own principles, he dealt with according to law and the forme thereof; And therefore I have not tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the law, <hi>but am an innocent man</hi> clearly appears by their own particular dealing with me, in that they never let me ſee, either Proſecutor, Informer or witneſſe, agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt me, nor never ſhewed me my Indictment, Charge or impeachment, no nor ſo much as face to face ever laid any manner of crime to my charge; See my narrative of their originall wicked Tyrannicall dealing with me, laid down in my Second Edition of the picture of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111285:3"/>
the Councel of State in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6 pag. of which, the Copy of their mittimus is recorded, which yet layes no<note n="(*)" place="margin">And their warrants ſince for my cloſe impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, runs thus (without any cauſe or crime expreſſed in them <hi>Die Mercurij 9</hi> of <hi>May 1649.</hi> Ordered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that there be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon all perſons from comming to Lieu <hi>Col.</hi> John Lilburne, <hi>M.</hi> Thomas Prince, <hi>M.</hi> William Walwin, <hi>and M.</hi> Richard Overton, except their wives and children and neceſſary ſervants, <hi>Hen. Scobel Cler. Parlie.</hi> and then the <hi>12</hi> of May <hi>1649.</hi> It is Ordered and Reſolved that we all four be reſtrained a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cloſe Priſoners, apart one from another in ſeverall lodgings in the Tower, but he were wiſe that knew wherefore.</note> crime to my charge, for it only commits me (Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> being one of the makers of it) <hi>for ſuſpition of treaſon, and names no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular act,</hi> and generals in law are nothing as appears in 2 par. inſtit. fol. 52. 53. 590. 591. 615. 616. and by the 1 par. Parl. book of Dec. pa. 38. 39. 77. 66 67 101. 123. 162. 201. 203. 277. 278. 845. ſee alſo the Armies Book of Declarations, pag. 70. and my Plea before the Judges of the Kings Bench the 8 of May 1648. called the Laws funerall pag. 8. 16, 17. 11. At which tryal by ſtrength of arguments, I forced the Judges openly to confeſſe, that generals are nothing in law; ſee alſo the 2 Edition of my Book of the 8 of June 1649. Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The legall fundamentall liberties of the people of England,</hi> revived, aſſerted and vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>pag.</hi> 5 21. all which rightly conſidered, it cleerly appears, <hi>I am an innocent man,</hi> in the eyes of thoſe very men that committed me, who never laid crimes in their lives to my charge to this preſent houre; And therefore I can ſtile it no better then Robbery and Felony in Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> Colonel <hi>George Fenwicke, &amp;c,</hi> ſeizing upon my eſtate with a <hi>Felonious</hi> intent, to deprive me of it, without any pretence, <hi>ſhadow or colour of law,</hi> and not only felony, but <hi>Treaſon it ſelfe in ſubverting our fundamentall lawes,</hi> higher then ever the Earle of <hi>Straffords</hi> was for which he loſt his head, who in his large additionall Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment, 1640. in the preamble of it, recorded in Speeches and paſſages of Parliament pag. 120. 121. 122. to 143. is impeached as a Traitor, <hi>for procuring inſtructions or commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the King, to him in the North of England, as Lord Preſident to heare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine cauſes, according to the arbitrary courſe of the Star-Chamber, in purſuance of which he the ſaid Earl in the month of May, in the 8 year of the ſaid King, and divers years following did put in practice the ſaid Commiſſion and Inſtructions, and did direct and exerciſe, an exorbitant and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull power and juriſdiction, on the perſons and eſtates of his Majeſties ſubjects in thoſe parts, and did diſinherit divers of his Majeſties ſubjects in thoſe parts, of their inheritances, ſequeſtred their poſſeſſions, and did fine, ranſome, puniſh and impriſon them and cauſed them to be fined, ranſomed, puniſhed and impriſoned, to their ruine and deſtruction, and namely, Sir</hi> Conyer Darcy, <hi>Sir</hi> Iohn Boucher <hi>and divers others, againſt the lawes, and in ſubverſion of the ſame; and that by virtue of the ſaid illegall Commiſſion he did moſt Traiterouſly ſtop the efficacy of all prohibitions, and</hi> habeas corpuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, <hi>and would not ſuffer any party to be diſcharged, till the party performed the Arbitrary De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce: and Orders of him and his aſſociates; and Traiterouſly to the ſubverſion of the fundamentall lawe of</hi> ENGLAND, <hi>and to the terrour of thoſe that adminiſtred them; did the</hi> 21 <hi>of March in the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 18 <hi>yeare at the open aſſiſes at</hi> Yorke <hi>ſay, that ſome of the Juſtices were all for Law, but they ſhould finde that the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> little finger, ſhould be heavier then the loynes of the Law; but the ſaid Sir</hi> ARTHUR HASLERIG, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> more arbitrartly and more trayterouſly then <hi>Strafford,</hi> having no pretence of <hi>REGAL, Legall</hi> or <hi>Parliamentary-Commiſſion</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> (no no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo much as from the preſent nothing or illegall <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCTO,</hi> or the preſent illegall thing called <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouncel of ſtate,</hi> that ever he produced or ſhewed) hath <hi>Feloniouſly and trayte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſly</hi> ſeiſed upon my eſtate, meerly by his own will and of ſet purpoſe, <hi>to ſtarve me and my family thereby,</hi> without any manner of, colourable pretence, and therefore abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h in law and reaſon more deſerve to dye then the Earl of <hi>STRAFFORD</hi> did, eſpecially conſidering he was one of his Judges, that in terrour and example to others ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111285:3"/>
and judiciouſly condemned him to the Scaffold for theſe very things; and this Arbitrary Power exerciſed in <hi>England</hi> by the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> is not only condemned &amp; judged<note n="(*)" place="margin">See the Act of his Attainder which ſaith, that he is impeached of high treaſon for endeavouring to ſubvert the ancient and fundamentall lawes and government of his Majeſties Realmes of England and Ireland, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce an Arbitrary and Tyrannicall government againſt law in the ſaid Kingdomes and for exerciſing a tyrannous and exorbitant power over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the lawes of the ſaid Kingdoms, over the Liberties, eſtates and lives of his Majeſties Subjects, for which he is adjudged and attainted of high Treaſon, and ſhall therefore ſuffer the paines of death, and loſſe of his estate. See this at large in the peoples Prerogative, pag <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but alſo the like in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as appears in the 3 article of his Impeachment; for that (as the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle ſaith) it was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by the ſame Lawes, where the Earle being Lord Deputy, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſubverſion of the fundamentall lawes there, did upon the 30 day of <hi>Septem.</hi> in the ninth year of the late King, in a publick Speech at <hi>Dublin,</hi> declare and publiſh that <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">Which very language is now growne ſo common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, that their little Beagles commonly yelp it out; See Maſter Prinnes Book, called a legall vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Liberties of England againſt illegall taxes and pretended Acts of Parliament, lately enforced on the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, pag. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> was a conquered Nation (and ſo ſay our great o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es here <hi>England</hi> now is) and that the King might do with it what he pleaſed, (as <hi>Oliver &amp;c.</hi> ſay they may do with this) And in his 4 Article he is impeached as a Traytor, <q>for arbitrarily ſtopping and prohibiting <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Corke</hi> the benefit of the Law, for recovery of his poſſeſſion, from which he was put by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of an Order made by the ſaid Earl of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rafford,</hi> and the Councel Table there, whom upon the 20 of <hi>Feb.</hi> in the 11 yeare of the late King, upon a paper petition, without a legall proceeding, he threatned to impriſon him unleſſe he would ſurceae his ſuit, and ſaid, that he would have neither Law nor Lawyers diſpute or queſtion any of his Orders, and further ſaid he would make the the Earl and all <hi>Ireland</hi> know ſo long as he had the government there; any act of State there made, or to be made, ſhould be as binding to the ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ects of that Kingdom, a an act of Parliament, and upon ſundry other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt <hi>Hoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ig</hi> like) by his words and ſpeeches, did arrogate to himſelfe a power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the fundamental<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lawes, and eſtabliſhed government of that Kingdom, and ſcorned the ſaid Laws and eſtabliſhed government.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in Article 6. he is impeached as a Traitor, <q>in that without any legall proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and upon a paper petition of <hi>Richard Ralſtone,</hi> he did cauſe the ſaid Lord <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Norris</hi> to be diſſeiſed, and put out of poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</q> (as the Truſtees for Biſhops Lands hath lately, but more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly, done my ſelf and my Landlord<note n="*" place="margin">Whoſe legal intereſt thereunto is thus: <hi>Nicholas Young</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquire, had a Patent from Biſhop <hi>Montague,</hi> about 30 yeers ſince, confirmed by the Dean and Chapter of Wincheſter, (which is unqueſtionably good in Law) for the keeping of the Manor of Wincheſter Houſe in Southwark: and not only ſo, but alſo for his life to enjoy all the profits, benefits, &amp;c. of the ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor houſe, gardens, orchards, and all things thereunto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as is largely ſet forth in the ſaid Patent: All which, upon ſpeciall view of <hi>Youngs</hi> Evidence by a ſelect Committee of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, hath been ſince ſolemnly confirmed by an Ordinance of a full, free and unqueſtionable Parliament about five yeers agoe; which Ordinance forced <hi>Deveniſh</hi> to pay <hi>Young</hi> as his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, for his un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eſtionable, legal and confirmed right in the ſaid houſe 52 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                  <hi>per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nun</hi> for the bare Manor Houſe; reſerving unto the ſaid <hi>Young</hi> as much beſides, as was worth about as much more <hi>per annum:</hi> all which right the ſaid <hi>Deveniſh</hi> bought for money of him, and M. <hi>John Cook</hi> drew up the conveyances; who hath often told me, <hi>Deveniſh</hi> his right was as good as either Law or Ordinance could make it: of which <hi>Deveniſh</hi> I took a Leaſe for three yeers, in caſe <hi>Young</hi> lives ſo long, for as much as I am to pay 13 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                  <hi>per annum:</hi> and yet by force of arms, without any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of proceedings at Law, by the command and wil of the ſaid T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uftees &amp;c. we are diſpoſſeſſed of our juſt and legall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions by the hands of the Sheriff of Surrey, who (if we could enjoy any Law, as in the leaſt we cannot) is liable to repay all our wrongs &amp;c. But for my part, ſeeing I live in a Land where Law and Juſtice is in words profeſſed, I am reſolved as ſoon to part with my heart blood, as in ſilence, ſlave and vaſſal-like, part with my legal and unqueſtionable right and poſſeſſion, although the Truſtees have lately ſold it (as it is ſaid) to M. <hi>Walker</hi> of Newington; which they have no more right to do, then ſo many theeves have to ſel the clothes of my back Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave Independent Juſtice! more abominable in their ways and doings, then all the currupt Intereſt that pretendedly for tyranny they have pulled down.</note> 
               <hi>Deve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> at <hi>Wincheſter</hi> houſe) <hi rend="margQuotes">of his free-hold and inheritance of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of TYMORE in the County of AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAGH, after he had two yeers quiet poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> In the 7 and 8
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111285:4"/>
Articles of which, are ſeverall other caſes of the like nature; as of <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Dillons, Adam</hi> Viſcount <hi>Loſius</hi> and <hi>George</hi> Earl <hi>of Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Mary Hibbots;</hi> which eighth Article conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in theſe words, <q>That the Earl in like manner did impriſon divers others of his Majeſties ſubjects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pretence of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Orders, Decrees, and other il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall commands by him made for preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Debts, titles of Lands, and other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in an arbitrary and extrajudiciall courſe upon paper Petitions to him preferred, and no other cauſe legally depending.</q> For aggravation of whoſe offences, in <hi>treaſonably</hi> ſubverting the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Laws and Liberties of England and Ireland, read the Maſculine ſpeech of Mr. <hi>John Py<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> againſt him, and the Argument of Solicitor <hi>S. John</hi> (now the pretended Lord chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas) againſt him, who toward the laſt end of his argument, by way of aggravation of <hi>Straffords</hi> crime in ſetting up an arbitrary Government, in the overthrow of the Law, ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Parliament is the repreſentation of the whole Kingdom, wherein the King as Head, your Lordſhips as the more noble, and the Commons the other members are knit together in one body politick; this crime of <hi>Straffords</hi> diſſolves the arteries and ligaments that hold the bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y together <hi>(viz)</hi> the Lawes: he that takes away the Laws, takes not away the allegeance of one ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bject alone, but of the whole kingdom.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>It was (ſaith he) made treaſon by the Statute of the 13 <hi>Eliz,</hi> for her time, to affirm, That the Laws of the Land do not binde the deſcent of the Crown; No Law, no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent at all. No Laws, no PEERAGE, no ranks or degrees of men; the ſame conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Its Treaſon to kill a Judge upon the Bench: <q>This kils not only the Judge, but the Judgment.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Its Felony to imbezell any one of the judiciall Records of the Kingdom: <q>This at once ſweeps them all away, and from all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Its treaſon to counterfeit a twenty ſhillings Piece: <q>Here's a counterfeiting of the Law; we can neither call the counterfeit nor true Coin our own.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Its Treaſon to counterfeit the Great Seal for an Acre of Land: <q>No property here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is left to any<note n="‖" place="margin">It was well ſaid in a Speech againſt the Ship mony Judges, <hi>Take from us</hi> (as the ſaid Judges by that Judgment had done) <hi>the propriety of our eſtates, our ſubſiſtence, and we are no more a people:</hi> Speeches and Paſſages of Parliament pag. 271.</note> land at all. Nothing Treaſon now, neither againſt King, NOR KINGDOM, no Law to puniſh it.</q> And therefore he concludes, in aggravation
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111285:4"/>
againſt <hi>Strafford,</hi> or any thing by way of Plea, advantage or excuſe that can be ſaid for him; <q>He that would not have others to have Law, why ſhould he have any himſelf? why ſhould not that be done to him, that himſelf would have done to others?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Its true, (ſaith he) <q>We give law to Hares and Deers, becauſe they be beaſts of chaſe: but it was never accounted cruelty or foul play TO KNOCK FOXES AND WOLVES ON THE HEAD AS THEY CAN BE FOUND, becauſe theſe be beaſts of prey.</q> 
               <hi>Out of thine own mouth</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>thou wicked ſervant, will I judge thee</hi> Luke 19 21. And ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Tit. 1.12, 13. <hi>One of themſelves, even one of their own prophets ſaid, The Cretians are alwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es Lyars, evill beaſts, flow bellies. This witneſſe is true.</hi> Therefore, I deſire Sir ARTHUR HASLERIG to conſider, that if he deſerves death that ſteals a ſheep or an o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. becauſe it is a tranſgreſſion of a Law, (which Law, I ſay, in it ſelf is unjuſt, for putting men to death for theft) what doth he deſerve that breaks not only that Law by theft, (as he hath done in ſtealing my goods) but breaks all the Laws of humane ſociety, by murder, plots and conſpiracies to take away the innocents lives? all which he hath done to me;</p>
            <p>Firſt, By endavouring to murder me by cruell and illegall impriſonment, and cloſe and barbarous impriſonment; for he was one of my unjuſt Judges, that for nothing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted me.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By conſpiracy<note n="(**)" place="margin">The puniſhment of Conſpirators ſaies <hi>Cook</hi> in his <hi>3</hi> Part Inſt. <hi>f. 222</hi> is five fold, <hi>1.</hi> That their bodies ſhall be impriſoned in the Common Goal. <hi>2.</hi> Their Wives and children amoved out of their houſes. Thirdly, that all their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Lands ſhall be ſeized into the Kings hands, and the Houſe waſted, and the Trees extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated. Fourthly, All their goods and chattels forfeited to the King. Fiftly, That they ſhall loſe the freedom and franchiſe of the Law. That is, <hi>1.</hi> They ſhall never be of any jury, or recognitors of aſſize. <hi>2.</hi> Nor ever be received for a witneſſe in any caſe That they ſhall never come into any of the King Courts, but make Atturneys if they have any thing to do there; do this is called a villa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nous indictment <hi>(in the 24. E. 3. f. 33 &amp; 27. aſſ. 53.)</hi> becauſe of the villany &amp; infamy, which they deſerve againſt whom it is given, and all is in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flicted by the Common Law. <hi>See alſo f. 143. 163. See alſo more to this purpoſe, 1</hi> part. Inſt. fol. <hi>294. and 2. part</hi> Inſtit. f. <hi>130, 237, 238, 562.</hi>
               </note> to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my life which is manifeſted by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring (in an extraordinary manner) by bribes to hire falſe witnes againſt me <hi rend="margQuotes">(as his mother <hi>Jezabel</hi> did againſt innocent <hi>Naboth</hi> tor his vineyard)</hi> to take away my life, and when the party would not conſent to his wicked and damnable conſpiracy, hee <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath cauſed him to bee moſt horribly whipped with ſcars and hundreds of ſtripes, by running the Gantlop from S. <hi>Iames</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to Charing croſſe although he was no Souldier, without ſo much as ever convict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him of any crime, yea or ſo much as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bringing him before, either pretended Marſhall or civill judicature, but meerly did it in a higher, Arbitrary, tyrannicall, trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly <hi rend="margQuotes">manner, then ever the Earl of <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> acting any of his treaſons, for which he loſt his head;</hi> all which the ſaid <hi>Haſlerig</hi> and his Aſſociats hath moſt barbarouſly acted and done with, and upon the body of Mr. <hi>William Blanke</hi> of Colemanſtreet Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, as he himſelf in Print notably declares, whoſe remarkable Narrative is already printed in <hi>Mercurius Militaris, numb.</hi> 3. which thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <p>
                           <hi>William May</hi> of the Generals Regiment of Horſe, and I being School fellows, he came unto me Febr. 17. and asked me if I and my Maſter were friends yet and I told him no; then ſaid he unto me, if you will be at Whitehall to morrow, I will help you to a place of credence; at which time I was there according to his appointment, and when I had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with him there, he had me into a Chamber where were many Officers of the Army,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111285:5"/>
as alſo Captain <hi>Story.</hi> Mr. <hi>Lavender,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Price,</hi> and Mr. <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> Shoomaker, where they offered to me and nine more an Oath of Secrecie, which is as followeth:</p>
                        <q>YOu ſhall ſwear by the four Evangeliſts, and by all things contained therein, that you ſhall faithfully diſcover all ſuch Engliſh Delinquents as are and ſhall be there, and this to any of the four Commiſſioners; So God you help.</q>
                        <p>And they offered us 10 <abbr>s.</abbr> advance, and 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> the month to be paid by the four Commiſſioners, whoſe names are <hi>Andrews, De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>eroy, Mountain, Atte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ny,</hi> and eight did take this Oath, but I and one <hi>William Hill</hi> in Col. <hi>Prides</hi> Company did refuſe it; 'After which, the ſaid <hi>William May</hi> did promiſe me to help me to be Barber to C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lonel <hi>John Hewſon,</hi> of which ſervice of mine he did accept, Febr. 20. 1647. For which Col <hi>John Hewſon</hi> did promiſe me 14 <abbr>
                              <hi>s.</hi>
                           </abbr> weekly and I after ſome weeks asking him for money was by him put off; and being in great want for money at a time when I was trimming Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> I made my complaint unto him, and he promiſed to ſee me paid.</p>
                        <p>And Sir <hi>Arthur Haſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rig</hi> did often tell me, but eſpecially on Munday April 23. that unleſſe <hi>Lilburn</hi> and <hi>Walwin</hi> were taken off, they could not bring about their deſign: for (ſaid he) they are great Politicians, and if they live we cannot carry on our deſign; for they are Obſtacles in our way; but (ſaid he) if they were taken off, then we ſhould car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on our deſign: And further he ſaid unto me, pry into their actions ſo far as you can, and make diſcovery unto us what they act, and who are chief Agents for them at the meeting at the Whal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bone in <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>hbury;</hi> and (ſaid he) if they will imploy you in any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations of theirs refuſe it not, but make diſcovery thereof unto us, and be ſure (ſaid he) to learn the depth of their conſultations, and if at any time (ſaid he) you ſhould be taken with the reſt of the Faction in your meetings yet I promiſe you, you ſhall be for a while kept in priſon, but you ſhall be releaſed under hand, and we will ſay that you made friends, or that you broke priſon, ſo that you ſhall be clear, and ſhall be ſatisfied for all your expence that you are at herein. And further he ſaid unto me, that if I would ſwear, or undertake to produce evidences that the forementioned men were privy to the conſultations of the Kings party, that then it ſhould be ſufficient<note n="(**)" place="margin">Mark <hi>Haſlerigs</hi> wicked, and bloodthirſtineſs after our inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent lives.</note> againſt them, and I ſhould be pleaſed, and they would conſider my trouble hereof. And at the ſame time I told him, I had an Order from the Lieut. Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> for my Maſter <hi>James Coc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ey</hi> to pay unto my Father 40 <abbr>
                              <hi>l.</hi>
                           </abbr> but he refuſed it; he de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>red of me to ſee the Order which I did ſhew unto him; and he ſaid, <hi>That when this was done, then he himſelf would ſee my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter pay the ſaid ſum of</hi> 40 <hi>
                              <abbr>l.</abbr> to my Father:</hi> And further he ſaid unto me, meet me to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morrow in St. <hi>Jamſes</hi> Park, which I did April 24. and then he carried me into the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Saint <hi>James,</hi> and when he had locked the door, he with Commiſſary Generall <hi>Ireton</hi> asked me, if I knew Mr. <hi>Almary, Bubal, Hartley James Edington, John Arrowſmith, Thomas Robbinſon,</hi> and I made Anſwer yes; then ſaid they unto me, Be here in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon walking; at which place I did meet: And ſhortly after Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> with Colonel <hi>Pride,</hi> and one Captain <hi>Pretty</hi> came unto me and had me up to Commiſſary Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Ireton,</hi> at which time Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> and Commiſſary Generall <hi>Ireton</hi> did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of me to conſent that my name might be inſerted in the Warrant for to ſeize upon my body, as Priſoner with the reſt that are ſpecified in the ſaid Warrant; for ſaid <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> you muſt be with the reſt ſeized upon as Priſoner unto us, or otherwiſe you will be ſuſpected; but ſaid he and <hi>Haſlerig,</hi> it ſhall not at all prove hurtful unto you, for you ſhal go only under the notion of a Priſoner unto us; upon which promiſe of theirs, I conſented
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111285:5"/>
that my name ſhould be inſerted in the Warrant, which was to this effect as followeth.</p>
                        <q>
                           <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                              <body>
                                 <div type="order">
                                    <p>Theſe are to will and authorize you to ſeize upon the bodies of <hi>William Blanke,</hi> juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, <hi>George A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>maner, William Senball, Iohn Arrowſmith, James Edington,</hi> and theſe you are to bring unto S <hi>Iames</hi> to be examined upon a preſent dangerous deſign againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, City, Kingdom and Army.</p>
                                    <closer>
                                       <dateline>
                                          <hi>Given under my Hand at S. Jamſes</hi> 
                                          <date> this 24. <hi>of Aprill,</hi> 1649.</date>
                                       </dateline>
                                       <signed>Henry Ireton.</signed>
                                    </closer>
                                 </div>
                              </body>
                           </floatingText>
                        </q>
                        <p>Forthwith there was commanded a guard of Muskettiers to goe with me for the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending of the aforeſaid men, which was done accordingly; and about twelve a clock at night was brought to S. <hi>Jamſes</hi> before Commiſ. Gen. <hi>Ireton,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig.</hi> Col. <hi>Pride,</hi> Capt. <hi>Pretty,</hi> Lieut. Col. <hi>Maſon,</hi> (who examined them upon queſtions of the buſines afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid). <hi rend="margQuotes">
                              <hi>Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerig and Commiſ. Generall <hi>Ireton</hi> would have had me to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt them, which I denied, for in the thing I had no knowledge, upon which they were forthwith releaſed; and Sir <hi>Arthur Haſleri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi> then after told me by my ſelf, except I would confeſſe theſe Papers to be mine I ſhould be Priſoner, the which I denying was committed Priſoner, Aprill 25, 1649. and was continued in priſon untill the 27. of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill 1649 untill 9. in the morning; And about that time I was then brought to the place commonly called <hi>Pelmel,</hi> or neer thereunto, and there was forced to run the Gauntlet for no other cauſe that I know of but for denying to ſwear againſt them, Mr <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> and Mr <hi>Walwin,</hi> and my refuſing to get any to ſwear againſt them, as Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> would have had me have done, and likewiſe that I did not witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the forementioned Gentlemen, and likewiſe for refuſing to take their Oaths.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Aprill</hi> 30. 1649.</date>
In teſtimony of the truth hereof I have ſet my hand and am ready to depoſe it upon my Corporal <hi>Oath</hi> before any Magiſtrate of <hi>England:</hi>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>William Blanks Junior.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Haſlerig</hi> and <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> &amp;c. by falſe witneſs, by <hi>Blanks</hi> means could not effect the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of my life; then do they or one of them imploy<note n="(a)" place="margin">Yea an Agent of the ſaid <hi>Haſlerigs</hi> and <hi>Crowwels</hi> called <hi>Richard Arnold</hi> a Hopman at the Blue Anchor in Thames Street neer Billinsgate, and a Member of the Knaviſh Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy called Mr. <hi>John Goodwins</hi> Congregation, upon the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change about the time that the Juncto's new Treaſon trap came out, gave his Inſtruction to Juſtice <hi>Cooper</hi> in Southwark, under pretence of friendſhip to come and viſit us on purpoſe by diſcourſe to inſnare us, and ſo to bear witneſſe againſt us, of which one that heard the Inſtructions given, out of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of our integrity againſt his particular Intereſt, came to the Tower and told us all, how and by whom, Major, or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>Cooper</hi> was appointed to come, the time when, and alſo the Subject and manner of his diſcourſe, who accordingly the next day came accompanied with our <hi>quondam</hi> friend Juſtice <hi>Hill</hi> once of <hi>Southwark,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Cooper</hi> eſpecially demeaned himſelf exactly according to his Inſtructions foretold to us; but being forewarned of his intended villany, and <hi>Arnolds</hi> plot to take away our lives, we were fitted for them, and within a few dayes after, we ſent for <hi>Cooper,</hi> and before divers honeſt people, opened to his face all <hi>Arnolds</hi> bloody deſigne upon us, to both their infamy and ſhame.</note> one <hi>Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Verney</hi> a <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndam Cavalier,</hi> and give him a Commiſſion to plot and contrive yea (and juſtifie him therein) the taking away my life, as app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ars by his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Letters.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:111285:6"/>
                  <head>For my eſteemed good friend <hi>Colonel Iohn Lilburne,</hi> at his Chamber in the Tower theſe preſent.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SInce my arrivall in England, I have endeavoured to finde out the ſeverall conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions and diſpoſitions of men, and I perceive the major part of thoſe I have diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed withall, are led more by their own fancies then reaſon; I am very much troubled to ſee how ſtrangely things are carried, "finding the Subject not at all eaſed or freed from oppreſſion: I pray informe me in any one particular thing, wherein England hath received any benefit ſince the warre began? "Oh this is a bleſſed reformation! Thoſe Books of yours which I have lately ſeen doth handſomely laſh them; I am joyfull to hear that we have ſome true Engliſh-men left that will ſtand for our Lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rties and juſt Rights. <hi rend="margQuotes">My earneſt deſire is to engage with ſuch a party, and to joyne with you and your friends in on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and the ſame thing, and to ſteer my courſe by your compaſſe, and I ſhall (to the utmoſt of my ability) further your deſigne in any thing, though it be with the hazard of my life, which I ſhould willingly ſacrifice for my Countries L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>berty:</hi> To the ſame intent and purpoſe I make my addreſſes to your ſelfe, imagining you to be the chiefeſt of thoſe (who are in a ſcornfull way by your and the common-wealths Enemies) branded with the name of <hi>Levellers.</hi> I never yet regarded much the malice of my enemies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I beleeve the like in you; therefore I am the more incouraged to joyne with ſuch: Excuſe I beſeech you for my liberall and true hearted<note n="(*)" place="margin">And yet a greater Juda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly villaine, never breathed upon the earth.</note> expreſſions by way of writing; It is a cuſtome that I am uſed to, &amp; cannot on a ſudden leave it. "I ſhall at any place or hour give a meeting to any of your friends to diſcourſe further of it, and then you will finde my complyance with you will be very acceptable, "for I love to advance and further all honeſt, lawfull and chriſtian like actions. But I fear (unleſſe you act more privately then you have formerly done) that all will come to nought, for yeſterday I accidentally heard of ſome that were employed in the Country to act for you, were taken and carried Priſoners to <hi>Oxford</hi> by ſome of Colonel <hi>Scroopes</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">Its a common ſaying a treacherous lier had need of a good memory, which <hi>Verney</hi> wonts; for at this time <hi>Scroops</hi> Regiment was at <hi>Salisbury</hi> in Rebellion againſt their Generall and Officers.</note> Regiment, the truth of this Report I cannot much aver, but I received my intelligence from a very credible hand; If it ſhould be ſo, you muſt be the more cautious hereafter, otherwiſe you will wilfully give up your lives as a prey to your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. <hi rend="margQuotes">I cannot as yet ſay we, becauſe I know not as yet whether I ſhall be received as a friend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you or no. I can aſſure you my friendſhip ſhall very much advance your buſineſſe, for I ſhall engage many friends in <hi>Buckinghamſhire</hi> (it being my Native Country) with me, I am confident to gayne the ſtrongeſt party in that Country in ſpight of Fate. And as for <hi>Oxfordſhire, Barkeſhire,</hi> and ſome part in <hi>Hertfordſhire,</hi> I can (by reaſon of my many friends) ingage a conſiderable party in all thoſe Countries, and prevail with others (that love to ſleep in a whole skinne) to be as Neuters.</hi> This I beeleeve deſerves thankes: <hi rend="margQuotes">But I can further advance your buſineſſe in a more conſiderable way, if I finde you have good and faithfull Councellors about you, and that you have Gentlemen that are well beloved, and well eſteemed in their Countryes, that can on a ſudden (as I ſhall do) bring three or four thouſand men into the field to back him that ſhould doe you ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111285:6"/>
If you can do ſo I ſhall make another proviſion to you, <hi rend="margQuotes">which is to gaine the City of Oxford for you, which you may conceive will be very difficult to do, and many more that do not know me. "But by my means I ſhall worke with my friends within the Towne as well as thoſe without, I am almoſt confident of gaining it. Then ſhall we be in a condition to furniſh our ſelves with Armes, and have a place of retreat upon any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> And untill ſuch a thing be done, it will not be wiſdome in any publickly to appear; You will conclude the like, or any rationall man, therefore my requeſt to you is, that you would ſeriouſly weigh and take into your conſideration this my Letter, "and returne me your abſolute anſwer by my Porter. But if I ſhould be ſo fooliſh as accidentally to ſpeak a word or ſo, he is ſo honeſt that it paſſeth no further, the experience I have had of him aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth me as much. Moreover if you ſhould require a longer time in returning me an anſwer of what I deſire "my lodging is in <hi>Alderſgate ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Trinity Court</hi> at one Maſter <hi>Edward Pearſe</hi> his houſe hard by <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> therefore whom you are pleaſed to ſend to me, may there finde me. But in theſe dangerous times we cannot be too cautious in our Company, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unleſſe I am well a aſſured" that they that ſhall treat with mee in your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, come really from you; I ſhall be very ſparing in unfolding my minde, <hi rend="margQuotes">therefore I pray ſend me a token in writing by my Porter, that he which ſhall come to me as from you, may deliver me the ſame token, then ſhall I not be ſparing to let him know my reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</hi> I dare not come to the Tower leaſt there ſhould be notice taken<note n="(*)" place="margin">And yet at the ſame time had <hi>Bradſhaws</hi> and <hi>Froſts</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to write this Letter, O pure Rogue!</note> of me. Thus have I in part made a diſcovery of my mind unto you (though to you not very well known) I am the more ſorry for it; For ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly all the acquaintance that ever I had with you, was in the Tower, where I had the happineſſe three or foure times to bee in your company, in my honored friend Sir <hi>Iohn Maynard</hi> his Chamber. I know not whether you may call me to mind or no, but really you wil finde a moſt truſty ſecret and a moſt obliging friend and ſervant of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>May thee</hi> 8th. 1648.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>THO. VERNEY.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>I beſeech you deale as freely with me as I have with you.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But returning a conſidering anſwer to this, judging the <hi>Author</hi> at the firſt view a Knave, I enquired of a Presbiterian friend of Sir <hi>Iohn Maynards,</hi> whether he knew the man or no, who told me that a <hi>quondam</hi> fellow priſoner of mine had lately ſent word out of the Low-Countries that this man was empl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yed by thoſe of <hi>Darby-Houſe,</hi> to lay a Trap <hi rend="margQuotes">to ſhip the Prince and ſend him over unto them to England to deſtroy him;</hi> but the next day being made a kinde of a cloſe priſoner by the reſtraint of my friends and inhabitants of the Tower upon my ſtayers ſtopt the originall of theſe following lines in my hand.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>For my eſteemed good friend <hi>Colonel John Lilburne</hi> theſe preſent.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY Porter was at the Tower this morning, thinking to have admittance in, but they would not ſuffer him; which hath much troubled me: but being well acquainted with this Gentleman one of the Coyners in the Tower, I have prevailed with him to deliver you this Note, beſeeching you to returne an anſwer of the former in writing,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111285:7"/>
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">The anſwering of which in any kind had apparently hazarded my life.</note> ſealed up, and this my friend will ſee that it firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſafe to my hand; I pray uſe meanes to burn my Letter, as I ſhall cruel yours for feare of the worſt, and you ſhall extreamly oblige a moſt faithfull Servitor of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>May</hi> 9th. 1649.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>THO. VERNEY.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>Much newes abroad, but I dare not commit to Paper.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon receeipt of this I was more confirm'd in my own mind he was a Cheat, but having not abſolute proofs of my thoughts, I judg'd it the moſt ſafe way for me to ſit ſtill and return no written anſwer, nor yet much reveal him: So with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two dayes after he ſent me a third Letter, the Copy of which thus followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>SIr by a Monyers meanes I gate leave to come in, thinking to have had the good fortune to have had an hours diſcourſe with you, <hi rend="margQuotes">but I found I could not obtaine my deſire with ſafety either for you or my ſelfe; upon that I departed, and leaving you this note, by the which you may the better know of my willingnes to engage with you, aſſuring you that my friendſhip ſhall be advantageous. My deſire is to receive a full anſwer of my firſt Letter, which I ſent by my Porter <hi>Ric. Vaughan</hi> whoſe name you have taken.</hi> If then inke and paper be kept from you, I am confident as yet your ſpeech is not nor I hope will not; therfore you may deſire a friend (whom you have a good confidence of) to treat with me in your behalfe, and I doubt not but to give him ſatisfaction, to your and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths good content. But as I told you in my firſt letter, ſo I do in this, which is, that unleſſe "I can receive a certaine token from you, that you really ſend him <hi>I</hi> ſhall be very ſparing in my diſcourſe. Yeſterday morning I received a Letter from one Maſter <hi>William Parkins,</hi> whom I do not all know, and in that he advertized me, "that he was deſired by your ſelf to ſignifie unto me that it was your deſire to have me ſpeedily to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pair into <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham-ſhire</hi> to engage my friends in your behalfe, and how that he was going thither him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. If that be true, I pray uſe a ſpeedy meanes add let me know aſmuch, and let me but receive a Letter from you to any one of quality in that County that is of your party that we may adviſe together, and you will finde that you have a moſt faithfull Servant of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>11 of May, 1649.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>THO. VERNEY.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>This M. <hi>Parkins</hi> ſpecified in his Letter, that I ſhould finde him at the <hi>George at Ailſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> where your friends and my ſelf ſhould meet and adviſe about ingaging the Country. IF I AM BETRAYD, I pray let me know the truth from you.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon the receipt of which third Letter, I was abſolutely of opinion, he was a <hi>perfect Knave</hi> and <hi>Cheat,</hi> and eſpecially by reaſon of the afore mentioned <hi>Parkins,</hi> who to my knowledge, is a Man I never ſaw nor heard of before. But with the Letter I received a Meſſage,</p>
            <p>That at ſuch a ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Tower, there was a Gentleman muſt needs ſpeak with me about earneſt buſineſſe; which I preſently judged to be the fore-mentioned <hi>Thomas Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney:</hi> and as I was going to him, I met accidentally a Gentleman formerly of the Kings party, and enquired of him if he knew one <hi>M. Tho. Verney</hi> a Knights Son or no: And he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111285:7"/>
told me, <q>that a Knight of the Kings party had lately told him, that Sir <hi>Edward Verney</hi> the Kings Standard-bearer had a ſon lately come from the Hague, which was looked upon to be a very odd, ſtrange, light kinde of fellow; but yet to the Cavaliers pretended to be ſome kind of Agent from the Prince.</q> Whereupon I told the Gentleman the grounds and reaſons wherefore I asked him. But this Reply increaſed more jealouſie in me, that this VERNEY was a perfect Rogue indeed: and ſo to VERNEY himſelf I went; who upon diſcourſe told me, he had formerly five yeers agoe been of the Kings party, and "that his Father was ſlain at Edg-hill, being the Kings Standard-bearer. So I told him, I had read three Letters from him, which he confeſſed he had ſent to me. But I alſo told him (having Mr. <hi>Walwyn</hi> and Mr. <hi>Overton</hi> with me) <q>I wondred how he durſt write ſuch lines to me as he did: But he asked, wherefore? I told him, "Becauſe he was a meer ſtranger unto me; and there were ſuch lines, as if were he not one of DERBY-HOUSE Agents, might coſt him his life</q> But he ſaid, he kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w me to be ſo honeſt I durſt do him no miſchief: And for being one of DERBY-HOUSE Agents, he as much abhorred them as I did: and I wonder, ſaid he, I having been in Arms for the King, how you ſhould imagine they would be ſo ſilly to truſt me with any of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets; which they muſt do if I were their Agent. <q>Sir (ſaid I) It is no wonder that wicked men make uſe of any inſtruments to accompliſh their baſe ends; and you having been for the King are the more likely to deceive other men, and the more unſuſpected to work their ends: and money, we all know, is ſo tempting a thing, that it will make men of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe ſpirits change their principles; yet, though it be to the deſtruction of their Fathers, and nigheſt Relations: and why you may not be ſuch a one, I have too plain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations to beleeve.</q> And for that part of the irrationability of their truſting you, having been a Cavalier, <q>Why may they not as well truſt and imploy you as their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, as Parſon KEM, who now is their active and hired Agent, as from very good hand, I fully know: although its notorious he was an active man laſt yeer in the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of Kent, and a notable Agent in the revolt of the Ships.</q> But Sir, to be plain with you, I tell you, <hi>You are a jaggling Knave,</hi> and I could finde in my heart to lay hold on you for a knave, and carry you pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ently before the Lieutenant of the Tower with your own Letters. And that you are a Knave. I have theſe informations to beleeve: <q>You were lately at the Hague at the Princes Court (which he confeſſed) and there you were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by ſome belonging to the Committee of DERBY-HOUSE, to lay a deſigne to get the PRINCE a ſhip-board, and ſend him for England to loſe his head: And this was ſent over by ſome exiled Presbyter Gentleman to his friends in London.</q> A Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of London and a Colonel told me this the other day: and a Gentlemen Cavalier bid me beware of you for a Knave: At which the Gentleman (with the impudenteſt face and undaunted countenance that I have ſeen) denyed all; but <q>confeſſed he knew Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon KEM, and did beleeve him to be a Derby Houſe Agent; and meeting with him the other day in Weſtminſter Hall, he did confeſſe that KEM told him.</q> Men reported aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much of him as I now told him to his face. But with his much reaſoning with my ſelf, Mr. <hi>Walwyn,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Overton</hi> (who went on purpoſe with me to him, as fearing he came either to ſtab or poyſon me in a cup of wine, or the like,) he juſtified his integritie; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping I would not ſo violate the Rules of ſocietie and man-hood, as to betray him, and ſo undo him and his friends, eſpecially <hi>my friend Sir</hi> JOHN MAYNARD, who he often pretended, was bound in grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bonds for him, before he could get his liberty, and to this day ſo continued. So telling him his own to the purpoſe, I left him for a Knave; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Mr. <hi>Walwyn</hi> eſpecially preſſed hard to have him laid hold of: But being deſirous yet to trace him a little further, for many reaſons I can give, I let him alone. But yet,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111285:8"/>
for my own ſafety, the next day before all my three fellow-Priſoners, I fully informed the Lieutenant of the Tower of the buſineſſe, before an Officer of the Army then Captain of the Guard, and deſired him to acquaint the Committee of State with that, for I had the Letters and told him I would produce and avouch them; and another time the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Tower (ſince I was cloſe) being in my Chamber I told him again of it, and proffered him the Originall Letters which he ſeemed not willing to meddle with, ſo I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſted ſince till the 29 of June laſt; upon which day I wrote a Letter to Maſter <hi>Hunt</hi> of Whitehall, and ſent him an exact Copie of <hi>Verneys</hi> foregoing Letters, and my foregoing Obſervations upon them, which Letter of Mr. <hi>Hunts</hi> I intreat you ſeriouſly to read in <hi>p.</hi> 8. of my <hi>Impeachment of High Treaſon againſt</hi> Oliver Cromwell <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not many daies after, Captain <hi>Den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> Serjeant at Armes to the thing called the <hi>Councel of State,</hi> came with a pretended Warrant to ſearch my Chamber, by whoſe hands (for a token I ſent an Exact Copie (of all I had ſent to Maſter <hi>Hunt</hi> of <hi>Verney<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) to his Maſter Mr. <hi>John Bradſhaw</hi> &amp;c. which although I have long ſince, as before you ſee, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and again acquainted <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> and other of <hi>Haſlerig.</hi> Aſſociates with VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEYS Letters, &amp;c. Yet the ſaid VERNEY continues as great with <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw</hi> and others, at the thing called the COUNCIL OF STATE to this very day, as if he were their ALPHA and OMEGA, which is a clear proof of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigningly ſetting him at worke whom they a little before ſent out by expreſſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in a Man of War to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; where at his coming to the Hague, he had preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as groundedly it is ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>) got ſomething like a Commiſſion from the Prince: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his Court diſcovered for a Traytor to him, he in haſte took his leave there; and <hi>at his departure ſhook hands with an a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quaintance of his, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id him farewell, he was in haſte, for he was betrayd.</hi> So coming into England, <hi>Haſleri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> &amp;c. having tempted by offered bribes the foreſaid honeſt M <hi>Blank</hi> to ſwear faſly againſt me, he and <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> or other of then brethren in evill, commiſſionated the ſaid villanous <hi>Thomas Verney</hi> to write Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to me, the which, if under my hand I had anſwered, or ſent a friend, as he deſired, to treat with him; then might they eaſily have ſearched his chamber, and there found ſome kind of Commiſſion from the Prince to the ſaid <hi>Verney,</hi> to authoriſe him to be his Agent in England, for which <hi>Verney</hi> might have been in ſome ſeeming danger, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendingly to ſave himſelf, might have produced my Letter, and alſo ſwore, according to the largeneſs of his conſcience, what he had pleaſed againſt me; which might have been look'd upon by <hi>Haſlerig</hi> and <hi>Bradſhaw &amp;c. as crime enough to have hanged me up without any more adoe, for correſponding with their declared Traytor the</hi> PRINCE, <hi>ſeeing they could not</hi> (as they earneſtly deſired) <hi>murder me any other way: and this act of</hi> Verney's <hi>ſhould have, to the eyes of the world, been merit enough to have ſaved</hi> Verney<hi>'s life, and alſo procured him his liberty from his Lords and Maſters</hi> Haſlerig <hi>and</hi> Bradſhaw <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who for his traiterous and good ſervices done them, protect him againſt all the complaints of cheating, perjury, forgery, and all manner of knavery that my intelligence tels on daily is brought in againſt him. Which <hi>Verny,</hi> a few dayes ago (as I am from extraordinary good hands informed) had the impudence, for all the high complaints againſt him, to petition (or otherwiſe to ſue for) an annuall Penſion for his good ſervices done them, in <hi>forſaking his Intereſt in the PRINCE, and adhering to Them in any thing they put him upon (though never ſo wicked)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Haſlerigs</hi> deſign in endeavouring to murther me is not only evident, in his Aſſociats impriſoning me for nothing, and ſo robbing me of my trade and credit, but alſo in cloſe impriſoning me from the ſociety of all my friends, and denying me the juſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111285:8"/>
and legall allowance due to me in my caſe and condition, (not one penny of which I have received to this day) but <hi>alſo in taking away compleatly betwixt</hi> 24 <hi>and</hi> 2500 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>that ſo I may not have a penny left to buy me my wife, or family a bit of bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eturne, I would fain have HASLERIG to <hi rend="margQuotes">conſider ſeriouſly from his friend S. <hi>Johns</hi> words, and the reſt foregoing what he deſerves, that not only by theft of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther breaks one of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> but endeavours to deſtroy, and actually plucks up by the roots the whole Fabrick of the Laws of England? and ſo deſtroyes HU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANE SOCIETY, by bringing all things into the originall Chaos of confuſion, and when he hath ſo done doubly and trebly, protects and ſecures himſelf by force of the <hi>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> and other <hi>tyrannicall Priviledges,</hi> from all manner of Proceſs of Law or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice truely he deſerves whereever he be found, to be dealt with as <hi>Felton</hi> did with the Duke of <hi>Backingham;</hi>
               </hi> which for my part I proteſt ſeriouſly, I judge to be more juſter both before God and man a thouſand times over, then Haſlerigs <hi>dealing with me,</hi> and the laſt and ultimate refuge and remedie that all ſuch men have in ſuch caſes, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more juſt then for a man to murder himſelf by fami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing in ſilence, by ſuch mens oppreſſive and tyrannicall de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling with him And if <hi>Strafford</hi> upon <hi>S. Johns</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned principles were A FOX and A WOLF <hi>for arbitrarily ſubverting the Law, and taking away mens prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ties and eſtates by proceedings upon Paper petitions;</hi> then abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>Haſlerig</hi> a FOX and a WOLF in <hi>arbitrarily ſubverting the Law, and taking away my eſtate, with wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e much as any proceedings at all,</hi> or any Paper Petition againſt me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo much as receiving and producing any pretended Commiſſion from any <hi>Legall,</hi> or pretended Magiſtracy ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>And therefore undeniably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom S. <hi>Johns</hi> and his own grounds may as a POLCAT, a FOX and a WOLF, yea and as a <hi>Deſtroyer</hi> of the ſociety of mankind <hi>he knockt on the</hi>
               <note n="(**)" place="margin">Read carefully for il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration hereof my Law-quotations in the Marginall note of the ſixt page of the late Impeachment of High Treaſon againſt <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> and his Son in law <hi>Henry Ireton.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>head where ever he is found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he had;</hi> which peradventure before much time may be expired may be for his portion, and that juſtifiably both before God and man, <hi rend="margQuotes">ſeeing no law in the world can be ſaid againſt him in the leaſt, or take hold of him:</hi> And therefore as in a Speech made, one thouſand ſix hundred and forty it is ſaid againſt the <hi>Ship-money Judges,</hi> Speeches and paſſages of Parliament <hi>page</hi> 275. Much more truly may I ſay now, when <hi rend="margQuotes">our Liberties are violated, our Fundamentall Laws abrogated, our Modern Laws already obſoleted, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of our Eſtates alienated, nothing left us we can call our own, but our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and our patience, if ever any Nation might juſtifiably, this certainly may now, moſt properly, moſt ſeaſonably, cry out, and cry aloud,</hi> VEL SACRA REGNAT JUSTITIA, VEL RUAT CAELUM, that is, <hi>Either let the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens fall, or let Sacred Juſtice reign.</hi> But if he ſhould deny that that which at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle</hi> he hath ſeized upon is none of mine, I prove my Legall right thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Admit I had in the eye of the law illegally come by it, yet being in poſſeſſion of it, he hath no pretence in the world to diſpoſſeſſ me of it, of his owne head, and by his own will; but 2ly I anſwer that againſt the law of equity, reaſon and Juſtice, yea, and the law of England. <hi rend="margQuotes">I was in the year 1637, 1638. 1639. 1640. moſt illegally and tyrannically dealt with by the High-Commiſſion, Councel-Board and Star-Chamber;</hi> by Doctor <hi>Guinne, Doctor Lambe, Doctor Ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and the Lord Keeper Coventry, Lord Privy Seal Mancheſter Lord Newberg, Old Sir Henry Vane, Lord Chief Juſtice Bramſton, and Judge Jones; And by the Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury, Lord Keeper againe, Lord Treaſurer Biſhop of London, Lord Privy-Seal</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:111285:9"/>
again, Earl of <hi>Arundel,</hi> Earl of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> Lord <hi>Cottington,</hi> Secretary <hi>Cook</hi> and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary <hi>Windebank</hi> and the <hi>Warden of the Fleet, who gagged me upon the Pillo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> without order in writing:</hi> Of which, the 3. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. being the firſt day the late diſſolved Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſate, I according to Law and Juſtice preferred my Petition and Complaint to to them; who upon the reading of my Petit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, <hi>immediately ordered me my Liberty,</hi> being, as I remember, the firſt priſoner in England ſet at liberty by them] <hi>to foll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w my Petition, and according to the legall cuſtom of Parliaments make i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good by proof</hi> before a ſelect Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee appointed by them to that purpoſe, Mr. <hi>Francis Reuſe</hi> having the hai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; before whom many particular dayes one after another<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I appeared with my Councel [being Mr. <hi>Robert Gurden</hi> brother to Mr. <hi>John Gurdon</hi> now Member of the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncto, or preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Houſe of Commons] and my Witneſſes, and fully proved all my Petition. Upon the report of all which by Mr <hi>Reus</hi> the Chairman, the Houſe of Commons the fourth of May 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> [being the very ſame day that the King himſelf cauſed me to be arraigned for high Treaſon at the Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of the Houſe of Pee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s] voted and reſolved upon the Queſtion,</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="declaration">
                        <p>
                           <hi rend="margQuotes">That the Sentence of Star-chamber given againſt JOHN LILBURN is illegall, and againſt the libertie of the Subject, and alſo bloody, cruell, wicked, barbarous, and tyrannicall.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Reſolved upon the Queſtion. <hi rend="margQuotes">That reparations ought to be given to M. LIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BURN for his impriſonment, ſufferings, and loſtes ſuſtained by that illegall ſentence.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>dered, <hi rend="margQuotes">That the Committee ſhall prepare this caſe of Mr <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>burns</hi> to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Lords, with thoſe other of Dr. <hi>Baſtwick,</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ctor <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>on,</hi> Mr <hi>Button</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pryn.</hi>
                           </hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>H. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ſinge Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>After which Votes (being in a full, free, <hi>un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aviſht,</hi> or <hi>inforc'd,</hi> legall, and unqueſtionable Parliament (after a <hi>full,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, <hi>free</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Where, I very well remember, Sir <hi>Arthur Hoſle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ig</hi> was one of my zealous and forward Judges; and when War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>James Ingram</hi> came to the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of the Court of Wards, and brought Maſter <hi>Herne</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uncellor to plead for the Lords, and in excuſe of himſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, who ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſly inſiſted in a high manner upon the orders and decrees of Star-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, upon which I very well remember Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> with a great deale of indignation ſaid unto <hi>Herne,</hi> I value not a Decree of the Lords in Star-Chamber a ruſh, if it be not expreſly according to the tenor of their commiſſion the Law, and I further tell you it is a ridiculous thing Sir to ſummon Parliaments to meet together to make Laws, if the Lords decrees in Star-Chamber againſt law ſhould be bind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng; and therefore, although you have proved for your Clyant Maſter <hi>Ingram</hi> that the Lords in open Court (the Court ſitting) commanded him on the Pillory to gagg Maſter <hi>Lilburn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> yet for ſpeaking againſt them, I tell you by law that order ought to have been in writing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtom of the Court, which you confeſſe it was not, and therefore Maſter <hi>Ingram</hi> muſt ſmart for his executing of orders on M. <hi>Lilburne</hi> made illegally.</hi>
               </note> and fan hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and examining of all my foreſaid ſufferings and complaints) troubles and the warres came on, and being in my own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, folly ſatisfied of the juſtneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments then cauſe, in the height of zeale accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with judgment and conſcience, <hi rend="margQuotes">upon the principles I have largely laid down in the 26. 27. 75. 76 pages of my book of the 8th of June 1649. intituled Englands le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, fundamentall, &amp;c.</hi> I took up Armes for them, and fought heartily and faithfully in their quarrel,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111285:9"/>
(for maintaining of which I had like to have been hanged at <hi>Oxford,</hi> while during my in priſonnment there, I loſt 5 or 600 <abbr>l.</abbr> out of my eſtate at <hi>London,</hi>) till the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſent Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> had like to have hanged me, for being a little to quick in taking in <hi>Tikell Caſtle,</hi> which ſpoyled a ſouldier of me ever ſince; after which in the year 1648. <hi>I
followed the Houſe of Commons cloſe to tranſmit my foreſaid votes to the Lords;</hi> which with much difficulty (occaſioned chiefly by Mr, <hi>William Prinne,</hi> and other his zealous Presbyterian frien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s) I got by peice-meales tranſmitted, where by reaſon of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> intereſt I might have expected long delay, yet I found quick diſpatch, <hi>and upon the</hi> 1 <hi>of December</hi> 1645 <hi>by ſpecially decree, they took off the fine ſet upon me by the Starchamber; and afterwards I got the whole vote tranſmitted,</hi> who at their open Barre, <hi>Judicially upon the</hi> 13 <hi>of February</hi> 1645. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed me a ſolemn hearing <hi>de novo</hi> of the whole matter, <hi>and aſſigned</hi> Mr. <hi>John Bradſhaw and</hi> Mr. <hi>John Cook for my counſell;</hi> who with abundance of witneſſes accordingly appeared, where Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> did moſt notably open the Starchamber injuſtice towards me, but eſpecially their<note n="(*)" place="margin">Whoſe very words all are recorded by <hi>M. John Cook</hi> in his printed Relation of that dayes proceedings before the Lords, who in the 3 page thereof upon the reading of the <hi>Star-chamber</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt me, moſt truly recites <hi>Mr.</hi> Bradſhaws obſervations in theſe very words; <hi>viz. that the ſaid ſentence was felo de ſe,</hi> guilty of its own death, the ground whereof being becauſe <hi>Mr</hi> Lilburne refuſed to take an oath, to anſwer to all ſuch que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions as ſhould be demanded of him; It being ſo contrary to the Lawes of God, Nature, and the Kingdom, for any man to be his own accuſer, and yet the ſame <hi>Mr.</hi> Bradſhaw after he hath moſt illegally taken away the Kings life and drenched his hands in his blood: commits me then to priſon for ſuſpition of Treaſon, meerely for refuſing to anſwer to a queſtion that he himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of me, as fully appears in the <hi>2</hi> edition of my picture of the Councell of ſtate <hi>pag 10. 11. 16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ex officio</hi> or interogatogatory proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with me and produced my witneſſes upon oath pun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctually to prove every head of his argument Upon which full hearing the Lords made a notable decree; <hi>and adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and declared tho ſaid proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the ſaid Star chamber, againſt the ſaid</hi> John Lilburn, <hi>to be illegall and moſt unjuſt and againſt the Liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and Law of the Land, and Magna Charta, and unfit to continue upon record.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not aſſigning me any reparations in that Decree (the doing of which the Houſe of Commons left unto them, and the Lords according to former cuſtome looked upon to be their right in law to do,) whereupon I got Mr. <hi>John Cook</hi> to draw me up that dayes work with moſt pregnant and notable aggravations, which I printed and preſented a few dayes after to every one of the Lords; praying their aſſigning me particular reparations according to Law and Juſtice out of the Eſtates of my unjuſt Judges, that had done me ſo much wrong; upon which new addreſſe to them they did upon the fifth of March 1645. order and decree; and aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be paid unto the ſaid <hi>John Lilburne</hi> the ſumme of ten thouſand pounds for his Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations which for many reaſons (as there being ayding in the warres to the King &amp;c.) they fixed upon the Eſtates reall and perſonall of <hi>Francis</hi> Lord <hi>Cottington,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Windebank,</hi> and <hi>James Ingram</hi> late Deputy Warden of the Fleet, and afterwards by an other Decree for the preſent levying thereof out of their lands <hi>at eight yeers purchaſe</hi> (as they were before the Warres,) <hi>with the allowance of Intereſt at</hi> 8 <hi>
                  <abbr>l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </abbr> per centum, per annum; in caſe of obſtruction; for all or any part of it;</hi> and to this purchaſe cauſed an Ordinance to be drawn up which fully paſſed their Houſe the 15 20 and 27. of Aprill 1646. and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards tranſmitted it to the Houſe of Commons, where by reaſon of my bloody adverſary old Sir <hi>Henry Vains</hi> Intereſts and of my impriſonment by <hi>Mancheſters</hi> means in the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of London it lay aſleep till the 1. of Auguſt 1648 at which time 7. or 8000. of my
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111285:10"/>
true friends in London, ſigned and cauſed to be delivered a Petition to the Houſe of Commons for my Liberty, and the paſſing of the ſaid Ordinance: which Petition is ſince printed, with the Speech of my true Friend Sir <hi>John Maynard</hi> upon it. And in reference to which Ordinance the Houſe made this Order:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Martis, <hi>1</hi> Auguſt <hi>1648.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <salute>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Sir JOHN MAYNARD.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Sir PETER WENTVVORTH.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Lord CARRE.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Col. BOSVVEL.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Col. LUDLOVV.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Mr HOLLAND.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Mr COPLEY.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>IT is referred to this Committee, or any five of them, to conſider how Colonel <hi>John Lilburn</hi> may have ſuch ſatisfaction and allowance for his ſufferings and loſſes as was formerly intended him by this Houſe.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Henry Elſynge Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Upon which Order I got the Committee to meet, and preferred a Petition to them, the true copy of which followeth <hi>in my addreſſe to every individuall Member, daied</hi> 4 <hi>of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1648. Upon which Petition, at my diſcourſe with them, the Parliament having diſpoſed of all that part of the Lord COTTINGTONS eſtate that I ſhould have had, unto the Lord SEY, and alſo compounded with Sir FRANCIS WINDEBANK'S heir; the ſaid Committee were pleaſed (ſeeing they judged it a difficult piece of work for me to get it proportionably from all or moſt part of my unjuſt Judges) to fix it intirely upon the Lord Keepers eſtate, as the principal guilty man: of which, when the young Lord COVENTRY <hi>his Son and Heir heard thereof in France,</hi> he came poſting to England as in a maze, fearing what ſuch a precedent might bring upon him, if his Fathers eſtate [then dead] ſhould be compell'd to make me ſatisfaction; he being ſo capitall in injuſtice, that if that courſe ſhould be taken, his eſtate left him by his Father [if it were trebled] would not ſatisfie for his Fathers palpable injuſtice committed in his life time. And <hi>Mancheſter</hi> being in the ſame Bryers with his Father, being as unjuſt as the other, and <hi>having a Brother (viz.</hi> George Montague) <hi>and other conſiderable Intereſts in the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> ſo plyed their friends there, that they put a ſtop to the ſecond reading of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Ordinance. Which I firſt fully underſtood <hi>by the Speakers means,</hi> then my great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended friend, who one day began to reaſon with a Member of the Houſe [and my ſpecial Friend] about the unreaſonableneſſe to fix my Reparations upon the eſtate of the decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord COVENTRY; nay, or to give me any Reparations at all out of the eſtates of thoſe perſons that did me wrong, for fear the precedent in time might reach to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; <q>for Sir, ſaid the <hi>Speaker,</hi> [as the Member told me] if my Son and Heir ſhould be liable in law to make ſatisfaction to all thoſe men [out of that Eſtate I ſhould leave him] that I have in the eye of the Law wronged [by ſigning Warrants, Orders and Decrees by the Command of my Superiours] he would ſoon be a begger, although I ſhould leave him 5 or 6000 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                  <hi>per annum;</hi> and therefore deſired, as it were, the ſaid Members concurrence with them; who ſee a neceſſity, both in juſtice, and for the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous importunity [as they called it] of me and my friends, to give me reparations; but yet to do it in ſuch a way, that the <hi>Precedent might not in future make themſelves ſmart for their injuſtice to particular men.</hi>
               </q> Of which, when the ſaid Member told me, and withall told me, they were reſolved to make the <hi>Common wealth my Pay-Maſter</hi> out of the publick Treaſury, and colour over the juſtneſs of it with this pretence, <q>That <hi>Cotting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> eſtate &amp;c. formerly aſſigned me, they had ſince diſpoſed of for the Common-wealths uſe, to the Lord <hi>Sey;</hi> and therefore now it would be no injuſtice to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth [although in the Star-chamber it never wronged me] to pay me my repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</q>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:111285:10"/>
Of all which, when I underſtood their deſigne, I was not a little troubled and perplexed in my ſpirit (although I was grown much into debt by reaſon of my long and chargeable ſufferings and large loſſes) to ſee that my ſufferings ſhould produce no benefit at all to the Common-wealth; which I muſt, as before God, in the ſincerity of my heart aver, was much in mine eye, <hi>no earthly Treaſure in the world being of that value to me, to make me undergo thoſe ſorrows and diſtreſſes that I underwent in the Biſhops time:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had I undertaken any hazards (and continued in them) out of any other conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. but <hi>out of conſcience and duty to God, and my native Country,</hi> I was much perplexed and raiſed up in my ſpirit, ſeeing the main end of my ſtruglings was like to be fruſtrated, which was, <hi>That the Nation might have good by it,</hi> by the creating of Precedents, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour for the future to Tyrants and Knaves; that ſo the people hereafter might live more in freedom and peace, in the enjoyment of their Laws and Liberties; the conſideration of which made me ſomething fearleſſe of my own particular welfare; and in my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe at their door, to ſet all my expectation on the Tenter-hooks: and a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collecting my thoughts, I modellized the fore-mentioned <hi>Addreſſe of the</hi> 4 <hi>of Sebtember,</hi> 1648, and printed it, and the next day (as I remember) with my own hands preſented it to every Member that would receive it, as they went into the Houſe: The true copy of which thus followeth;</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To every individuall Member of the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</head>
                  <head>The Humble Remembrance of Lieut. Col. <hi>JOHN LILBURN,</hi> Septemb. <hi>4. 1648.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>VOuchſafe to take notice and ſeriouſly to conſider, That the firſt week this preſent Parliament ſate, which is now almoſt full 8 yeers agoe, I preſented a <hi>humble Petition</hi> to the Houſe of Commons, for juſtice and right againſt the cruell Judges of the <hi>high Commiſſion Court,</hi> and the Star-chamber, and I had the honour [the ſame day it was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented) <hi>to be one of the firſt priſoners in England that was ſet at liberty by this Parliament,</hi> and alſo received a ſpeedy, full, fair, and candid proceeding, in the hearing and examining of my tyrannicall ſufferings: but by reaſon of multiplicity of publick buſineſſe, and other great obſtructions, I have not as yet been able to attain to the full end of my legall and juſt expectation and right, viz. <hi>Reparations</hi> for my long, ſad and tormenting ſufferings by the foreſaid unjuſt and unrighteous Judges.</p>
                  <p>Be pleaſed alſo favourably to take notice, <hi>That upon the firſt of Auguſt laſt, there was an humble Petition preſented to the Honourable Houſe of Commons, ſubſcribed by many thouſands of honeſt citizens, &amp;c</hi> humbly to deſire you to put me in the <hi>fall poſſeſſion</hi> of all your <hi>be-paſt juſt Votes</hi> about my foreſaid ſufferings: upon reading and debating of which Petition, as in anſwer to that particular of it, your Houſe were pleaſed to make this enſuing Order.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="memorandum">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Martis, <hi>1</hi> Auguſti <hi>1648.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <salute>Lord <hi>Carre,</hi> Sir <hi>John Maynard,</hi> Sir <hi>Peter Wentworth, Col. Boſwell, Col. Ludlow,</hi> M. <hi>Copley,</hi> M. <hi>Holland.</hi>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>IT is referred to this Committee, or any five of them, to conſider how Col. <hi>John Lilburn</hi> may have ſuch ſatisfaction and allowance for his ſufferings and loſſes as was formerly intended him by this Houſe.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Henry Elſing Cler. Dom. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:111285:11"/>Unto which ſaid Committee at their firſt ſitting, I preſented a Petition; the copy of which thus followeth.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                     <body>
                        <head>To the Honourable the Committee of the Houſe of Commons appointed to conſider of Lieut. Col. <hi>Lilburns</hi> buſineſſe in reference to the Star-chamber: The humble Petition of Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
                        <p>THat beſides your Petitioners ſufferings by reaſon of his baniſhment into the Low Countries, he was firſt committed by D. <hi>Lamb, Guin, Ayle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>,</hi> 1637. and afterwards had 3 yeers impriſonment in the common Gaole of the Fleet, <hi>being whipt from Fleet-bridg to Weſtminſter,</hi> and enduring the cruell torment of <hi>above five hundred ſtripes with knotted cords:</hi> afterwards being ſet in the Pillory for the ſpace of two hours; and by <hi>James Ingram</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty Warden of the Fleet, <hi>gagged, tearing his jaws almoſt in pieces,</hi> without Order: which Sentence was given by Lord Keeper <hi>Coventry,</hi> Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> Lord Privie Seale, Lord <hi>Newburgh,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Vane ſenior,</hi> Lord chief Juſtice <hi>Brampſton,</hi> and Judge <hi>Jones.</hi> And after the barbarous execution of this Sentence, being April 18. 1638. the ſaid Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> Arch biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> Earl of <hi>Arundel,</hi> Earl of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> Lord <hi>Conington,</hi> Lord <hi>Newburgh,</hi> Secretary <hi>Cook,</hi> and <hi>Windebank,</hi> paſſed another Sentence, in effect, for the <hi>Starving of your Petitioner,</hi> and for the tormenting of him with <hi>irons upon both hands and legs both night and day; and by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him cloſe in the comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n Gacle of the Fleet from the ſpeech of any of his friends:</hi> all which was executed with the greateſt cruelty that could be <hi>for the ſpace of almoſt three yeers toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> to the apparant hazard of his life, both by ſtarving him [which was with all art and induſtry ſeverall wayes attempted;] and alſo by ſeverall aſſaults made upon him by the ſaid Wardens men [inſtigated thereunto by the ſaid Deputy Warden, to the maiming and wounding him, whereby to this day he is totally deprived of the uſe of two of his fingers:] All which, with much more, too tedious to be here inſerted, was fully proved by ſufficient witneſſes, before a Committee of your Houſe, whereof M. <hi>Francis Rous</hi> had the Chair; upon whoſe report made May 4. 1641, your Houſe voted, <q>That the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the Star-chamber given againſt the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> and all the proceedings thereupon, was illegall, and againſt the liberty of the Subject, and alſo bloody, wicked, cruell, barbarous and tyrannicall; and that he ought to have good Repa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</q> Which Votes (by reaſon of multiplicity of buſineſſe in your Houſe) coſt your Petitioner ſome yeers of importunate and chargeable attendance to get them tranſmitted to the Lords; <hi rend="margQuotes">which was obtained in February 1645. the 13 day of which month your Petitioners whole cauſe was effectually opened at the Lords Bar,</hi> by his learned Councel M. <hi>John Bradſhaw,</hi> and M. <hi>John Cook;</hi> and there every particular again proved upon Oath, by teſtimony of people of very good quality; whereupon they concurred in all things with the Houſe of Commons, ſaving in the matter of Reparation; But upon the delivery of a true narrative, the Copy whereof is hereunto annexed, (which your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with his own hands in the ſame month delivered unto every individuall Lord) they made a further Decree, that your Petitioner ſhould have 2000 <abbr>l.</abbr> reparations out of the eſtates of the ſaid Lord <hi>Cottington,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Windebank,</hi> and <hi>James Ingram,</hi> for the reaſons alledged in an Ordina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ce which they paſſed in April 1646, and tranſmitted to your Houſe, where it hath lain dormant ever ſince, and is now referred to the conſideration of this Honorable Committee.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="21" facs="tcp:111285:11"/>Now, foraſmuch as by the judicial Laws of God <hi>(which are the pure laws of right reaſon) he that wilfully harteth his neighbour,</hi> is bound to the performance of theſe five things: Firſt, <q>If it be a blemiſh or wound, Like for like, or to redeem it with money, thereby to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie him for his wound. Secondly, For his pain and torment. Thirdly, "For the healing. Fourthly, "For his loſſe of time in his calling. Fifthly, "For the ſhame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace;</q> all which are to be conſidered according to the quality of the perſon damnified: which reparations are to be paid out of the beſt of the goods of him that damnified him, <hi>and that without delay.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And as the Law of God, ſo the Laws of this Nation doth abhorre, and hath ſeverely puniſhed (above all perſons) Judges many times with the loſſe of their<note n="‖" place="margin">
                              <hi rend="margQuotes">See notably to this purpoſe thoſe pregnant inſtances in my Epiſtle to my nick named Levelling friends, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually meeting at the <hi>Whalebone</hi> in <hi>Lothbury</hi> behind the Exchange, dated From my cloſe impriſonment in the Tower of London, the 17 of July, and recorded in my Impeachment of high-Treaſon againſt <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 6. 7. 8.</hi>
                           </note> lives and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, <hi>who under colour of Law, have violated their Oaths, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the lives, liberties and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the People, whom by law they ſhould have preſerved:</hi> as may be inſtanced by the 44 Judges and Juſtices <hi>hanged in one yeer</hi> by King <hi>Alfred;</hi> divers of them for leſſe crimes then hath been done in this caſe of your Petitioner; as may be read in the Law-book, called <hi>The Mirrour of Juſtice,</hi> pag. 239. 240. 241. &amp; tranſlated and re-printed this very Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and by Juſtice <hi>Thorp</hi> in <hi>Edw</hi> the third his time, who was condemned to death for the violation of his Oath, for taking ſmall ſumms of money in Cauſes depending be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; as appears in the 3 part of <hi>Cooks Inſtitute, fol.</hi> 155.156.</p>
                        <p>And by the Lord chief Juſtice <hi>Treſilian,</hi> &amp;c. who in full Parliament in <hi>Rich.</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds time was attached as a Traitor in the forenoon, and had his throat cut at <hi>Tyburn</hi> in the afternoon, <hi>becauſe he had given it under his hand that the King might create unto himſelf as his pleaſure, another rule to walk by then the Law of the Land preſcribes him;</hi> as appears by the Parliament Records in the Tower, by many of your own Declarations, and alſo by the Chronicles of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Now foraſmuch as your Petitioners ſufferings hath <hi>been unparalel'd,</hi> and his prejudice ſuſtained thereby altogether <hi>unrepatrable;</hi> having <hi>loſt his limbe,</hi> &amp;c. And foraſmuch as by the Law of God, Nature and Nations, <hi>reparations for hurts and damages received, ought to be ſatisfied as far as may be in all perſons,</hi> though done by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cident and not intentionally, and though through ignorance: much more when the Perſons offending, <hi>did it knowingly,</hi> and <hi>on purpoſe</hi> in the <hi>face,</hi> nay, in the ſpight of the <hi>fundamentall Laws of the Land,</hi> which they were ſwoon to preſerve: And for that the reparations in the ſaid Ordinance aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed doth <hi>ſcarce amount</hi> to what your Petitioner <hi>ſpent in his three yeers ſad captivity,</hi> and his now almoſt <hi>eight yeers chargeable attendance,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n ſuing for it, beſides the loſſe of <hi>a rich and profitable trade for eleven yeers together, and his wounds, torments, ſmart and diſgrace, ſuſtained by his ſaid Tyannicall ſentences.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>He therefore humbly prayeth the favour and Juſtice of this honorable Committee <hi>for ſome conſiderable augmentation of his ſaid Reparations,</hi> and the rather, becauſe his fellow ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer Doctor <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſtwick</hi> had 4000 <abbr>
                              <hi>l.</hi>
                           </abbr> reparations alotted him, whoſe ſufferings (he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively conceiveth) was nothing nigh ſo great, in <hi>torment, pain</hi> and <hi>ſhame,</hi> as your Petitioners) And foraſmuch as the now Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> ſon and heir to the foreſaid Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> hath walked in his <hi>Father, Steps, in enmity to the Laws Liberties, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Nation;</hi> by being in <hi>arms</hi> at the beginning of the Wars againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111285:12"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="21" facs="tcp:111285:12"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="22" facs="tcp:111285:13"/>
and made his peace with the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> for a ſmall matter, &amp; hath ſince <hi>diſened</hi> the Kingdom, living in <hi>France</hi> privately, receiving the profits of <hi>a vaſt eſtate</hi> which his Father left him. And foraſmuch as his ſaid Father (the late Lord <hi>Coventry</hi>) was the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt man in infringing the Laws and liberties of the Nation; although <hi>a Lawyer and Judge,</hi> ſitting on the ſupream ſeat of juſtice, and a perſon (as is groundedly conceived) who got a great eſtate by corruption, and particularly a man that principally paſſed, as chief <hi>Judge of the Court,</hi> both the aforeſaid ſentence againſt your Petitioner: And in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the eſtates of the ſaid Lord <hi>Cottington,</hi> and Sir <hi>Francis Windebank,</hi> by ſubſequent orders of both Houſes upon urgent occaſions are <hi>much intangled and altered from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition they were in,</hi> in 1646<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when the Lords ordered your Petitioner 2000 Marks out of them, and for that the eſtate of <hi>James Ingram</hi> cannot be found, nor at preſent come by. Your Petition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r therefore moſt humbly prayeth, <hi>That the greateſt part if not all your Petitioners reparations</hi> may be fixed upon the ſaid now Lord <hi>Coventries</hi> eſtate, to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly paid your Petitioner; or elſe that his <hi>Rents,</hi> and the profits of his <hi>woods</hi> and <hi>goods</hi> may be ſeized in the reſpective Counties where they lie, for the ſatisfying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; that your Petitioner may no longer run the hazzard of ruine to him and his, by te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious delaies, <hi>having already contracted the debts of many hundreds of pounds, occaſioned by the chargeable proſecution hereof:</hi> And that if you ſhall think of conjoyning any other with him, That it may be principally the <hi>Judges of the Law;</hi> who ought to have been <hi>Pilots</hi> and <hi>guides</hi> unto the reſt of the Judges of that Court, who were <hi>Lords,</hi> and perſons not knowing the Law.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray,</hi> &amp;c. JOHN LILBURN.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>After the reading of which they entred into a ſerious debate of the whole buſines, and thereupon <hi>paſſed ſeverall Votes to be the Heads of an Ordinance</hi> to be drawn up and reported to the Houſe, by the Right Honourable the Lord <hi>Car</hi> Chairman to the ſaid Committee, who accordingly reported the proceedings and votes of the ſaid Committee to your Houſe, who approved of the ſaid Votes, and ordered an Ordinance <hi>to be preſented to the Houſe conſonant thereunto,</hi> which was accordingly done by the Lord <hi>Car,</hi> which Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance hath been once read in your Houſe: The Copie of which thus followes:</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Parliamentary_ordinance">
                     <body>
                        <head>An Ordinance of the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, for the raiſing of three thouſand pounds, out of the reall Eſtate of the late <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> late Lord Keeper of the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> for and towards the reparation and damages of <hi>John Lilburn</hi> Gent. which he ſuſtained by vertue and colour of two Sentences given and made againſt him, in the late Court of <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> the one the <hi>13.</hi> of <hi>Febr. 1637.</hi> the other the <hi>18.</hi> of <hi>April, 1638.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>WHereas the cauſe of <hi>John Lilburn</hi> Gent. concerning two Sentences pronounced againſt him in the late Court of Star Chamber, 13 <hi>Febr.</hi> 13 <hi>Car. Regn.</hi> and 18. <hi>Apr.</hi> 14 <hi>Car. Regis,</hi> were voted the 4. of May 1641. <hi>by the Houſe of Commons to be illegall, and againſt the Liberty of the Subject, and alſo bloody, wicked, cruel, barbarous, and tyrannical,</hi> (which were tranſmitted from the ſaid Houſe of Commons, unto the Houſe of Lords; who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, by an order or decree by them made, 13 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1645. <hi>Adjudged do declared</hi> the ſaid proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the ſaid <hi>Star chamber,</hi> againſt the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> to be <hi>illegall, and moſt unjuſt, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the liberty of the Subject,</hi> and <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> and unfit to continue upon <hi>Record,</hi> &amp;c. And by another Order or Decree, made by them the ſaid Lords, the 5. of <hi>March</hi> 1645. they aſſigned to be paid unto the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> the ſum of two thouſand pounds for his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111285:13"/>
reparations; and the ſaid <hi>Houſe of Peers</hi> then fixed that ſum upon the eſtates <hi>reall</hi> and <hi>perſonall,</hi> of <hi>Francis</hi> Lord <hi>Cottington,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis VVinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank,</hi> and <hi>James Ingram,</hi>
                           <note n="(**)" place="margin">
                              <hi rend="margQuotes">But the Lord <hi>Roberts,</hi> the Lord <hi>Wharton, &amp;c.</hi> told mee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall times, if their eſtates had not been under Sequeſtration by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have gone about to fix my repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by Ordinance (which they muſt needs then doe to take off the Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration) but have iſſued out a decree and extent under the great Seal, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly to have put me in preſent poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of my 2000 <abbr>l.</abbr> which they ſaid was their right by Law to doe.</hi>
                           </note> late Deputy War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Fleet: and afterwards for the preſent levying thereof, <hi>with allowance of Intereſt, in caſe of Obſtructions,</hi> while the ſame ſhould be in levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and of ſuch part as ſhould not be forthwith levyed; The ſaid Houſe of Peers did cauſe an Ordinance to be drawn up, and paſſed the ſame in their Houſe, the 27 <hi>Aprill</hi> 1646. and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards tranſmitted the ſame to the Houſe of Commons for their concurrence; with whom it <hi>yet dependeth.</hi> And for as much as ſince that tranſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſion, all or the greateſt part, of the <hi>eſtates</hi> of the ſaid Lord <hi>Cottington</hi> and Sir <hi>Francis Wind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>k,</hi> is ſince by both Houſes diſpoſed of to other uſes, and the eſtate of the ſaid <hi>James Ingram</hi> is ſo ſmall and weak, and ſo <hi>intangled with former ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>umbrances,</hi> that it can afford little or no part unto the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> of the ſaid reparations. And for that the ſaid late Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> was the principall <hi>Judge,</hi> and chief <hi>Actor,</hi> in giving of <hi>both</hi> the ſaid <hi>Illegall</hi> Sentences in the ſaid Court of Starchamber; and for the <hi>barbarous</hi> inflicting of puniſhments thereupon:</p>
                        <p>Therefore, and or ſatisfaction of the ſaid 2000 <abbr>
                              <hi>l.</hi>
                           </abbr> and for the increaſe of reparation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> for his <hi>extraordinary</hi> wrongs, <hi>ſufferings</hi> and <hi>loſſes</hi> thereby ſuſtained, <hi>and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ong time hitherto elapſed without any ſatisfaction.</hi> The Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament do ordain, and be it hereby ordained by the ſaid <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> and by Authority of the ſame, <hi>That the ſaid</hi> John Lilburn <hi>ſhall receive the ſum of</hi> 3000 <hi>
                              <abbr>l.</abbr> out of all or any the Mannors, Meſuages, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments,</hi> whereof he the ſaid late <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> or any other perſon or perſons to or for his uſe, or in truſt for him, was or were <hi>ſeized in fee-ſimple, or fee taile, or otherwiſe,</hi> at the <hi>time</hi> of the ſaid ſentences or decrees, or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>either</hi> of them, in the ſaid late <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> or ſince within the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Dominion</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> any Order o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Ordinance heretofore made by either or both Houſes of Parliament for the imployment of the eſtate of the ſaid late <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Coventry</hi> to the contrary hereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding. <hi>And for the more ſpee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ly levying of the ſaid ſumme of three thouſand pounds,</hi> It is further Ordered and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, That the ſeverall and reſpect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ve <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> of the ſeverall and reſpective <hi>Counties,</hi> within <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> wherein <hi>any</hi> of the ſaid Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments doe <hi>lye,</hi> ſhall forthwith upon <hi>ſight,</hi> and by <hi>vertue</hi> of this Ordinance <hi>cauſe an inquiſition to be made,</hi> and taken by <hi>the oathes of twelve or more lawfull men, where the ſame lands do lie,</hi> and what the ſame are and do contain, and of the <hi>clear yearly value thereof,</hi> over and <hi>above all</hi> charges and re-priſes; and after ſuch inquiſition ſo made and taken, the ſeverall and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> ſhall deliver unto the ſaid <hi>John Lilburne</hi> true copies in <hi>Parchment</hi> of the ſame <hi>inquiſitions</hi> by them taken, and ſhall then alſo <hi>deliver</hi> unto the ſaid <hi>John Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>burn</hi> the ſaid Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments which ſhall be ſo compriſed or mentioned in the ſaid inquiſitions, <hi>To have and to hold,</hi> to him the ſaid <hi>John Lilburne</hi> and his <hi>aſſignes</hi> without <hi>impeachment of waſte;</hi> and untill he ſhall have received out of the iſſues and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits thereof (to be eſtimated according to the yearly values contained in the ſaid inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) the ſaid ſumme of <hi>three thouſand</hi> pounds; <hi>together with all reaſonable charges and expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be ſuſtained from henceforth for obtaining the ſaid ſumme of three thouſand pounds:</hi> And all and every the ſaid ſeverall and reſpective <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> and all other perſon and perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111285:14"/>
that ſhall <hi>any wayes act or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſſiſt in obedience to this Ordinance,</hi> according to the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and meaning thereof, ſhall be therefore <hi>defended</hi> and kept <hi>harmeleſſe</hi> by the authority of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Be pleaſed further to take notice, That after the foreſaid Ordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ance, was once read, it came to a debate in your Houſe for to be read the ſecond time, which was carried in the negative by majority of voices; and I cannot but apprehend that were divers in the houſe unſatisfied in the Ordinance it ſelf, in regard the Houſe was divided upon the debate and Vote, which I cannot but apprehend muſt flow from one of theſe two conſiderations.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Either becauſe that the whole reparations is fixed upon the Lord <hi>Coventries</hi> eſtate <hi>ſingly;</hi> who had many <hi>co-partners</hi> in the ſentences, <hi>and who alſo it may be ſuppoſed hath expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated his crime by his death.</hi> Or elſe ſecondly, Becauſe in ſome mens thoughts, ſome of my late actions are or have been ſo evill in themſelves, that they may ſeem to them to <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballance the merrits of all my ancient ſufferings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the firſt of which, beſides the reaſons contained in the foregoing Petition, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly crave leave to offer theſe unto your judicious conſideration.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, I have by almoſt eight years<note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi rend="margQuotes">Viz. the Earle of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisbury,</hi> but eſpecially old Sr. <hi>Henry Vane</hi> that notorious and guilty Traitour, that betrayed all the North of <hi>England</hi> to the Earl of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle,</hi> the particulars where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you may at large read in <hi>Englands</hi> birth-right pag. 19 20, 21. and in my Reſolved mans Reſolution, April 1647: pag. 14. 15, 16. 17, 18. See alſo the 2 Edition of my picture of my fore-mentioned book of the eight of June 1649: pag. 19. 20. and the Impeachment of high Treaſon againſt <hi>Cromwell.</hi> pag. 6.</hi>
                     </note> dear-bought experi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce, found the intereſt of ſome of my fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned <hi>potent Judges</hi> (who yet ſit in both houſes of Parliament) <hi>to be too ſtrong for me to grapple with</hi> (and the onely cauſe in my apprehenſion that hath all this while kept me from my own) and therefore my own intereſt (which compels me ſtrongly to endeavour by all juſt wayes and means to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to my juſt end reparations) neceſſitates me as much as I can to wave the fixing upon them.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I continually finde amongſt the greateſt part of my Judges an apprehenſion, in their own ſpirits, that in <hi>conſcience</hi> and <hi>equity</hi> there ought to be <hi>favour</hi> ſhewed to thoſe of my <hi>Star-chamber</hi> Judges that have <hi>joyned with the Parliament</hi> and Kingdom, rather then to thoſe that have fought and conteſted againſt them both, <hi>and that ſeeing the latter are able enough in Eſtates to make ſatisfaction, it ought in conſcience and equity ſoly to lie upon their heads;</hi> and I being not to guide or command my Judges, but rather to be in this guided and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by them, and to acquieſs in their reaſons they give me, eſpecially when my own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding tels me they moſt conduce to the obtaining my main end, which is juſtice in the poſſeſſing of my own. Now theſe things conſidered, and conjoyned to the reaſons laid down in my foregoing Petition, I ſubmiſſively conceive, as things now ſtand, <hi>in Law, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and conſcience,</hi> no juſter objecton can be found for you to fix my reparations upon <hi>then the reall eſtate</hi> (whereever it is to be found) of the late <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> who was the Principal Actor in this bloody <hi>Tragedy:</hi> and who was not leſſe eminent in cruellty then in place, being <hi>judge</hi> of the higheſt ſeat of mercy, the Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which ought to abate the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edge of the Law, when it is too <hi>keen:</hi> Now for the chief<note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi rend="margQuotes">Read carefully Mr. <hi>Iohn Cooks</hi> moſt remarkable aggravations in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned relation of my ſufferings at the Lords bar <hi>Febr.</hi> 13. 1645. p. 8, 9.</hi>
                     </note> Judge of mercy to degenerate into a ſavage cruelty, not heard of amongſt the Barbarians, nor to be read of in the Hiſtories of the bloodieſt Perſecutors, how tranſcendently hainous and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable is it?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:111285:14"/>And though he be dead, <hi>yet juſtice lives;</hi> and whatſoever is become of him, his eſtate ought to make ſatisfaction, according to the rule of his own court of <hi>Star-chamber, he that ſuffers not in his body, muſt ſuffer in his purſe.</hi> And therefore I may juſtly expect my reparations <hi>out of his reall eſtate that he was poſſeſſor of at his death,</hi> where ever I can now find it; whether it be in the poſſeſſion of the preſent <hi>Lord Coventry,</hi> or others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and you may there as <hi>righteous Judges</hi> fix it for theſe reaſons;</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Becauſe the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> late <hi>Lord Coventries</hi> reall eſtate, in equity, if not in the eye of the Common law, <hi>ought to ſatisfie his debts, though dead;</hi> though now it be in the poſſeſſion of the preſent <hi>Lord Coventry,</hi> &amp;c. and in reaſon &amp; conſcience there is at leaſt as much equity that it ſhould <hi>repair injuries,</hi> eſpecially of <hi>ſo high a nature</hi> as mine is of; and the rather, if it be conſidered that the late <hi>Lord keeper Coventry</hi> had, beſides his reall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, a very conſiderable <hi>perſonall eſtate at his death,</hi> which I deſire not to meddle with, although it be deſcended to his heirs, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Becauſe the eſtate now in the hands of the ſon and heir, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the late Lord Keeper <hi>Coventry</hi> deſcended from him, and was in the <hi>hands of the ſaid late Lord</hi> Keeper <hi>Coventry</hi> himſelf, at <hi>the time and ſome years after his</hi> paſſing the forementioned <hi>two illegall and barbarous ſentences againſt me.</hi> Now in caſe I could have injoyed the benefit of the Law then, or immediately after they were paſſed againſt me, <hi>I might by an action of the caſe have had at Law ſatisfactory damages out of his eſtate:</hi> And if there was any Law or equity for reparations to be given me out of his eſtate then, the <hi>equity</hi> and <hi>juſtice</hi> of the caſe is nothing altered by the ſaid late Lord <hi>Coventries deceaſe,</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> of the <hi>ſame estate</hi> to the preſent Lord <hi>Coventry</hi> his ſon or others.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Becauſe the late <hi>Lord keeper Coventries</hi> paſſing ſuch ſentences as he did againſt me, was [as may appear by the Votes of your own Houſe, made in the caſe, 4. <hi>May,</hi> 1641.] <hi>a ſubverſion of the Fundamentall Lawes and Conſtitutions of the Land,</hi> and in the caſe of the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> that was adjudged <hi>Treaſon:</hi> And in the caſe of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>the Law doth diſ-inherit and diſ-franchiſe all the poſterity of any one adjudged guilty thereof;</hi> therefore my reparations (for tranſcendent injuries done, in ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary caſe,) out of the eſtate of the Father, though it be deſcended to the Son, or Sons, &amp;c. is <hi>no injury</hi> to them in <hi>equity nor conſcience:</hi> neither do I conceive, that in caſe this Parliament ſhould impoſe a Fine <hi>of ten-times as much as my reparations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount unto,</hi> out of the aforeſaid late Lord <hi>Coventries</hi> vaſt eſtate, to be paid to the publike purſe of the Kingdome, for the ſatisfaction of the <hi>publike Juſtice</hi> thereof, and <hi>the expiation of his notorious and ſuperlative crimes,</hi> could not in the leaſt, in equity reaſon and conſcience, be eſteemed unjuſt in the eye of any impartiall, righteous, or juſt man in <hi>England;</hi> and ſo much in anſwer to the firſt Objection.</p>
                  <p>And now with all reſpect to the juſt honour of Parliament, <hi>a word or two to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond:</hi> which is, <hi>That it may be in ſome Parliament mens thoughts, the evill of ſome of my late actions may weigh down the merit and deſert of all my ancient ſufferings;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to quit ſcores with me, without paſſing my Ordinance for <hi>Starchamber</hi> reparation, <hi>is too large Justice (in the ſtrictneſſe of Juſtice) for me?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which with all modeſty and reſpect, I Anſwer:</p>
                  <p>Admit my late actions were as vile, and as puniſhable, as by the worſt of my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies can be ſuppoſed to be, <hi>yet there can be no Justice in quitting ſcores with me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;</hi> and the reaſon is, <hi>becauſe, that were not only to puniſh me for good actions done,</hi> which my ſufferings againſt the <hi>Starchamber</hi> was, and was almoſt <hi>eight years ago</hi> ſo adjudged by your own Votes: but it were alſo <hi>to acquit and gratifie the guilty and</hi> obnoxious, which the preſent Lord <hi>Coventry</hi> [upon your own principles] <hi>is;</hi> as well as his Father was: and the Spirit of truth ſaith, <hi>To juſtifie the wicked, and to condemn the righteous, is both an abomination in the ſight of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:111285:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:111285:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:111285:16"/>Secondly, I anſwer: <hi>It is not now ſeaſonable for me to juſtifie my ſelf,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Yet I have ſince that do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e it with justification, as you may clearly and fully read in the ſecond Edition of my book of the eighth of June, <hi>1649.</hi> intitulled, <hi>The legall fundamentall Liberties, &amp;c. p. 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30. &amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> but rather to intreat you to do me juſtice and right, in paſſing my preſent Ordinance, without any more delay, for my reparations; <hi>wherein I have deſerved well, by your own often and ancient confeſſions,</hi> before ever you had any pretence of evill to fix upon me, or lay unto my charge; and when you have ſo done, if for any ſubſequent actions, any of you be offended again with me, I will put you in ſufficient and good ſecurity to anſwer the Law, without interceding for mercy or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion: But O if you be men of gallantry, juſtice, honeſty, or conſcience, puniſh not my poor and afflicted <hi>wife,</hi> and tender <hi>babes</hi> for my pretended tranſgreſſions, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing <hi>them to famiſh, or eat one another, by keeping my own from me,</hi> which ſhould preſerve them alive, voted unto me by your ſelves, almoſt eight years ago; and when you have done, do your pleaſure with me, even whatſoever ſeems good in your eyes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then expoſe me to <hi>ſee my deareſt Conſort, and the tender off-ſpring of our wombs, to periſh before my eyes;</hi> which I muſt ingeniouſly confeſſe, the ſtrength of duty, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall indeared affections, will not inable me to behold, with patience and ſilence: So deſiring God to direct your hearts, now at the laſt, to doe juſt and righteous things to me, and the Kingdome, <hi>for juſt and righteous ends;</hi> I take leave, in ſincerity, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe my ſelfe,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From the Tower of</hi> London, <date>
                           <hi>this</hi> fourth of Septem. 1648.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Yours to the laſt drop of my heart-blood, (if either you be Gods, or your Countreys,) <hi>JOHN LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <q>Nevertheleſſe we according to his promiſe, look for new heavens and a new earth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in dwelleth righocouſneſſe, <bibl>2 Pet. <hi>3.13.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </q>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon the preſenting of which, my Ordinance was called for to be read the ſecond time, which <hi>Elſynge the Clerke</hi> pretended he had laid ready upon the table before him; but what betwixt his <hi>knavery,</hi> old <hi>Henry Vanes,</hi> the <hi>Speakers,</hi> and young <hi>Mountagues,</hi> my Ordinance <hi>was ſtoln, and could never after be found:</hi> ſo that I was ſent to out of the Houſe to get another fair copie writ over preſently, which being long in doing, my friends went away, not expecting it would any more be medled with that day; ſo that when moſt of them were gone, my adverſaries took the advantage to call for it, and in a thin Houſe read it the ſecond time, and upon debate threw it out of doors, and at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſtop my mouth, voted me 300.<abbr>l.</abbr> ready money (as they pretended) out of Sir <hi>Charls Kemiſh</hi> his Compoſition, to inable me for preſent ſubſiſtence, and to follow my buſineſſe, and alſo made this further Order,</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Die Martis, Septem.</hi> 5. 1648.</head>
                        <p>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that the <hi>ſum of three thouſand pounds be allowed and paid unto Lievtenant Colonell</hi> John Lilburne, <hi>for reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his damages ſuſtained by colour of the ſentences given against him in the late Court of Star-Chamber,</hi> where <hi>Lord Carr</hi> hath the Chaire, with the addition of Sir <hi>John Danvers,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Rigby,</hi> to conſider of, and preſent to this Houſe <hi>an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for ſetling of Lands to him and his heires, to the value of</hi> 3000.<abbr>l.</abbr> 
                           <hi>at twelve
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111285:16"/>
yeers purchaſe,</hi> out of the eſtates of <hi>new Delinquents</hi> In the Inſurrections, not yet ſequeſtred.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>H. Elſynge,</hi> Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Of which when I fully underſtood, I was troubled, but knew not how to help myſelf, and having already met with ſo many difficulties, and received ſo manie baffles, as I had done, <hi>I thought it was better</hi> (being almoſt wearied out with ſtrugling) <hi>to take half a loaf, then go away without any bread at all:</hi> ſo I addreſſed my ſelfe to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, who left me to my choice to <hi>fix my reparations upon what Delinquents I thought fitteſt,</hi> that were not already diſpoſed of, and ſome of them told me of an Order the Houſe had made againſt Sir <hi>Henry Gibbs</hi> (who had a good eſtate in the County of Durham) upon an information M. <hi>Aſhurſt, and the reſt of their Commiſſioners from</hi> Scotland, <hi>had brought them;</hi> upon which they made this Order.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Die Luna, Aug.</hi> 28. 1648.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that the eſtate of Sir <hi>Henry Gibbs,</hi> reall and perſonall in England, be forthwith ſequeſtred.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>H. Elſynge, <hi>Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Upon conſideration of which, and my <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncles</hi> being <hi>Committee-men</hi> in the ſaid <hi>County of Durham,</hi> I then judged it moſt fitteſt for me, for the ſpeedy diſpatch of my buſineſſe (without any more <hi>baffles, delayes,</hi> or <hi>cheats</hi>) to fix in that County, and accordingly I got my foreſaid Committee to write a Letter to them; the copy of which thus followeth:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>For their honoured friends the Committee of Sequeſtrations in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> or to any <hi>three</hi> of them.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IT being by an Order of the Houſe of Commons of the fift of this inſtant, referred to us to conſider of, and to preſent unto them an Ordinance for ſetling of Lands upon Lievtenant Colonell <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> and his heirs, to the value of <hi>3000.<abbr>l.</abbr> at twelve years purchaſe,</hi> out of the eſtates of <hi>new Delinquents</hi> in the inſurrections not yet ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred; we (that we may be the better inabled to performe this ſervice) do deſire you, or ſome three or more of you, to make Certificate unto us in writing with all convenient ſpeed, of the names of ſuch Gentlemen, or others in your County, who have been emixous and knowne Delinquents (or ſo proved before you) in theſe late inſurrections, as alſo a particular in writing of their eſtates, and of the clear yeerly value thereof <hi>(communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus annis)</hi> over and above all charges and repriſes, and what termes and eſtates they have therein, and what incumbrances lie thereupon, as farre as can come to your knowledge, and to ſend by this Bearer <hi>Lievenant-Col. John Lilburne</hi> that Certificate ſealed up unto us, who are</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Dated at Weſtminſter,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Septem. 9. 1648.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Friends and Servants. Charles Carr, John Maynard, Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Rigby, Godfrey Boſwell, Edmond Ludlow, Lionel Copley, Corneliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Holland.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:111285:17"/>With which Letter, I immediately took a long, tedious, and chargeable journey into the North, and brought back an anſwer; the copy of which thus followeth:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>To the right honorable the Lord <hi>Charles Carr, and the reſt of the Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons, appointed to conſider</hi> the ſatisfaction of Lievtenant-Col. <hi>John Lilburne:</hi> Theſe preſent.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WE received your Honours Letter dated the ninth of September last, for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying the names and estates of ſuch new Delinquents as have been in the late inſurrections, wherein we have laboured as much as we can to informe our ſelves to give you ſatisfaction in your deſires, and therefore have ſent up theſe ſeverall Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates here incloſed of the names of ſuch perſons as have been Delinquents in theſe late inſurrections, amongst whom is Sir <hi>Henry Gibbs,</hi> for whoſe ſequeſtration we have received a peremptory Order from the <hi>Lords and Commons of Sequeſtrations,</hi> dated the <hi>28.</hi> of Auguſt last; the other two are openly known to have been in theſe late warrs: We have alſo ſent particulars of the yearely values of their eſtates in this County, ſo neere as we are able to learne, conſidering the ſhortneſſe of the time allowed by the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of the Bearer concerned therein, and the fewneſſe of us, who are now left to attend the ſervice of the Sequeſtration in this County, being no more that will act at all, then we whoſe names are hereunto ſubſcribed; we reſt,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Durham,</hi> 
                           <date>
                              <hi>October 12. 1648.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Your Honours humble Servants, Thomas Midford, Richard Lilburne, George Lilburne.</signed>
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>Which forementioned Certificate in brief thus followeth; A rentall of Sir <hi>Henry Gibs</hi> Lands in <hi>Jarro, in the County of Durham</hi> above the repriſes, for any thing we can find by examinations of the immediate Tenants of the ſaid Lands in <hi>Octob.</hi> 1648.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Jarroe with the grounds thereunto belonging</hi> 222.<hi>
                              <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum,</hi> belonging to <hi>Thomas Bows</hi> Eſquire (which he had with his wife) Octob. 1648. at <hi>Broadwood, Hareup, Pawſe, Meadowes, Stotley, Riding, Birkcloſe, and Land in Medelton field, Foggerforth, and Evenwood,</hi> 308.<abbr>
                              <hi>l.</hi>
                           </abbr> 10.<hi>
                              <abbr>s.</abbr> per annum</hi> (But as I remember, Evenwood being 80.<abbr>l.</abbr> 
                           <hi>per annum</hi> proved to be his brother <hi>Cradocks,</hi> and ſo reſteth 228. <abbr>l.</abbr> 10. <abbr>s.</abbr>) belonging to Sir <hi>Henry Bellinham at Beamount hill, in the County of Durham, Octob.</hi> 1648. <hi>copy-hold, and worth</hi> 180. <hi>
                              <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Thomas Midford.</item>
                                 <item>Richard Lilburn.</item>
                                 <item>George Lilburn.</item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </postscript>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>After I came to London with this, and delivered it to the Committee, they were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling I ſhould fix upon Sir <hi>Henry Gibbs his Land at Jarroe,</hi> to make over to me, and to my heirs for ever, for my 3000. <abbr>l.</abbr> allotted, and accordingly drew up an Ordinance, and truly what with the perſonall Treaties vigorous going on, which rendred the making over ſuch lands to be very dubious in the poſſeſſing of them, and the taking away his eſtate for ever, without viſibly declaring any particular cauſe, or ever ſo much as ſummoning him to anſwer, for the Crimes the Parliament Commiſſioners (privately in their houſe) laid to his charge, upon which they ſequeſtred him, (though I confeſſe I my ſelfe before rid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto Scotland to inquire of him, and had enough to ſequeſter him) <hi>or in default of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance legally to outlaw him;</hi> all which laid together, with other things following, I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111285:17"/>
had no ſtomack to his, or any other Delinquents Lands, knowing no reaſon why Sir <hi>Henry Vane, &amp;c. ſhould ſhift off from themſelves my reperations, for the tranſcendent injuſtice they had done me,</hi> and lay it upon the ſhoulders of thoſe in an extraordinary manner, that never particularly had done me wrong, (and beſides force me to put it to a dubious hazard, whether I ſhould injoy it or no) and underſtanding that Sir <hi>Henry Gibbs</hi> had an impropriation in the ſaid County, amounting to about 70. or 80. <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>per an. beſides a legall and juſt right in a great deal of wood in Bransboth Park, ſome part of which was ready feld, and ſo would make ready money, upon all which conſiderations, &amp;c.</hi> in as plauſable a manner as I could, I drew up a Petition to the foreſaid Committee to avoid the ſetling upon me the ſaid Lands, the copy of which followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the honourable the Committee of the Houſe of Commons, appointed to conſider of Lievtenant Colonell <hi>John Lilburns</hi> buſineſſe, in reference to the Starchamber.
The humble Petition of Lievtenant Colonell <hi>John Lilburn.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>THat upon ſeverall debates of the Petitioners barbarous ſufferings by the Starcham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in both Houſes of Parliament, <hi>The Houſe of Lords were pleaſed the</hi> 15. 20. 27. <hi>of April</hi> 1646. <hi>to paſſe an ordinance that your Petitioner ſhould receive</hi> 2000.<hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations out of the Lands of the Lord Cottington, &amp;c. at eight years purchaſe and upon the humble Petition of your Petitioner, to this honourable Committee in Auguſt laſt,</hi> for augmentation of his reparations, you were pleaſed for the reaſons therein alledged, <hi>to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>te your Petitioner</hi> 3000. <hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> for his Reparations, to be raiſed out of the eſtate of the now Lord Coventry in money,</hi> upon the report of which to the Houſe of Commons, by the right honourable the Lord <hi>Carr,</hi> the Houſe were pleaſed to <hi>confirm the ſaid Vote,</hi> and upon the Lord <hi>Carrs</hi> preſenting an Ordinance to the houſe to that end, <hi>the Houſe paſt it once,</hi> but before it could be read twice, either by the careleſneſſe or willfullneſſe of Mr. <hi>Elſynge the Clarke,</hi> your Petitioners Ordinance <hi>was imbeſled and toſt,</hi> and a new copy the ſame day was drawne and preſented to a thin Houſe, who threw it out of doors, <hi>and ordered your Petitioner to receive</hi> 3000. <hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> at</hi> 12. <hi>years purchaſe, out of the Lands of new Delinquents,</hi> which 3000.<abbr>l.</abbr> in effect and ſubſtance is not one 6.<abbr>d.</abbr> more, <hi>then the Lords</hi> 2000. <hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> was,</hi> the Lords 2000. <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> being at 8. years purchaſe, <hi>and the Houſe of Commons</hi> 3000. <hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> at</hi> 12. <hi>years purchaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That upon the laſt ſitting of this Committee, <hi>you were pleaſed to write to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Sequeſtrations of the County of Durham,</hi> to make Certificates to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the eſtates of new Delinquents in their County, <hi>who by their Letter and Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates of the</hi> 12. <hi>of October preſent, certifie of the clear delinquency of Sir</hi> Henry Gibb <hi>Knight, Sir</hi> Henry Bellingham <hi>Knight and Baronet, and</hi> Thomas Bows <hi>Eſquire,</hi> all of whom have reall eſtates in the ſaid County of <hi>Durham,</hi> the obtaining of which Certificate, coſt your Petitioner a tedious and chargeable journey into thoſe parts.</p>
                  <p>That your Petitioner, for divers weighty reaſons in his own thoughts, <hi>fixed princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally upon the eſtate of Sir</hi> Henry Gibb: but having been with divers and ſeverall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours learned in the Law of England, <hi>he clearly finds that in Law ſtrictly, his nor no other Delinquents Lands, can immediately be made over abſolutely to your Petitioner, and his heirs for ever, without ſuch clauſes of reſervation, as may totally indanger your Petitioner within a few moneths to loſe the fruit of his almo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t eight yeares extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary chargeable attendance,</hi> for juſtice in the premiſes in your Houſe, the termes of the conveyance in law being ſo tickliſh, <hi>that your Petitioner would not willingly give one yeares purchaſe for land ſo conveyed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore, and in regard your Petitioner cannot believe, <hi>that your Houſe intends
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111285:18"/>
him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fiction without a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſubſtance;</hi> for his already <hi>twice voted</hi> 3000.<hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> reparation, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> humbly prayeth, that he may receive your honourable aſſiſtance for the immediate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of an Ordinance, for your Petitioner to receive</hi> 8. <abbr>l.</abbr> per centum per annum <hi>for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> forbearance of his money, from the hands of the Committee of Sequeſtrations of the County of Durham, ariſing out of the eſtates ſequeſtred in the ſaid County of the ſaid</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Henry Gibb, Sir Henry Bellingham, <hi>and</hi> Thomas Bows <hi>Eſquire,</hi> beginning at the 25. of March <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt paſt, and that the <hi>reſidue of the profits of the lands, woods or other goods of the forſaid perſons, lying in the ſaid County, may as they ariſe go to the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Petitioner his ſaid</hi> 3000. <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> till it be fully paid, with an aſſurance unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ner, that in caſe any, or all of them compound with the Parliament for their delinquency, <hi>that ſo much of your petitioner reparations as thou ſhall remaine, may be ſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ed and paid out of their compoſitions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>And your Petitioner ſhall pray, &amp;c. <hi>John Lilburne.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich Petition of mine the Committee granted, and cauſed an Ordinance accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to be drawn up very fully, <hi>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly my back friend</hi> John Blaxſton <hi>and my unkle</hi> M George Lilburne <hi>being ſorely falled out,</hi> the man indeavoured to revenge himſelfe of me, and buſled ſo hard againſt me in the Houſe, as that he got all conſideration for the fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e forbearance of my money daſht out: which I was fain to beare with patience at the preſent, being not able to help my ſelf; and as I remember it was read and paſt the ſecond time, <hi>but the ſtreame of the Houſe running after the perſonall Treaty,</hi> with the ſuppoſition or jealouſie of divers of my acquaintance (and former friends amongſt thoſe men) that I had too deep a hand in the late London Petition of 11. September 1648. which ſeemed to them to be a choak peare to the Treaty, and they conceiving that I ſtill purſued the ſame ends, made the chariot wheels of the finiſhing of my Ordinance to got heavier then they uſed to do; ſo that for my blood I totally could not get fit to paſſe the Houſe of Commons in October 1648. and other buſineſſe of the Army coming on, I <hi>left looking after my Ordinance,</hi> and viſibly and totally, devoted my ſelf to an induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous indeavour to ſee if I with any other nicknamed levelling friends, could prevent ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cheat by the Army (who promiſed faire in their large Remonſtrance from S. <hi>Albans</hi> of 16. Novemb. 1648. pag. 66, 67, 68. but eſpecially in their moſt remarkable Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhewing the reaſons of their laſt advance to London) the true narrative of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with them and their friends you may read in the 2. edition of my book of the 8. of June 1649. intituled <hi>The legall fundamentall Liberties of the People of England received, aſſerted and vindicated,</hi> pag. 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38. which pages I intreat you ſeriouſly to read; and with them I continued very diligently and cloſely following them, to ſee if it were poſſible to get them conſent <hi>to the ſetling of the Kingdome upon the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and foundations of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of true freedom and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, by an</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The ſpeedy doing of which they both publikely and privately, as ſolemnly promiſed and ingaged to perform as almoſt it was poſſible for men to doe, as clearly you may fully read in their two laſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Declarations, but eſpecially that of the reaſons of their laſt advance to London, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but ſhort I have herewith ſent you, and intreat you moſt ſeriouſly to peruſe, as a cleare and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting teſtimony againſt their preſent wretched and apoſtatized baſeneſſe.</note> Agreement of the People that had not fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Freedoms; <hi>the onely and alone juſt cure of all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands maladies, not onely in my thoughts then, but ſtill at this preſent day;</hi> but when I appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and viſibly ſaw their <hi>jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and cheating,</hi> of which I with out feare told them, as you may read in pag. 39, 40. of my laſt named books. I ſay at the perceiving of their baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111285:18"/>
I judged it Impoſſible for me ever to get my Ordinance fully paſſe, unleſſe I would be their ſlave and vaſſall, which <hi>Harriſon, Sir William Conſtable,</hi> and Sir <hi>Hardreſſe Wader</hi> at their firſt coming to Whitehall laboured to get me to be, and to ingage my pen for them; but my poſitive anſwer to them all three face to face (in their chamber) was, <hi>That I would as ſoon ingage for the Turk as for them, unleſſe they would come to a righteous center where they would fixedly acquieſce, before they ſo much as attempted the medling with thoſe great things they intended, as the breaking the Houſe, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off the Kings hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> I ſay, perceiving they were reſolved to be knaves in the higheſt, and to go through with their intended reſolutions what ever it coſt, I thought it beſt for me to ſtir before all their fears and troubles were over, to get my Ordinance fully to paſſe before they fully got up into the throne, being confident if I ſtaid till they had got their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> buſineſſe about the King over, I ſhould never get it paſſe then, <hi>but upon implicit ingagements to be their ſlave, which I us much abhorred as I did the cutting of my own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and therefore I put pen to paper and write a netling Letter to the Speaker about it, being reſolved to <hi>lay my bones at their door</hi> in the purſuit of it, and its effect it had, for as I remember the next day my Ordinance was tranſmitted to the Lords, the copy of which Letter thus followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>M. <hi>Speaker,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THough I cannot challenge much intereſt in you, yet being a ſuffering oppreſſed <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh-man,</hi> and conſidering you in the place you are in, I cannot chooſe but in black and white preſent you with a little of my ſorrowes, which I aſſuredly know is now as eaſie for you to redreſſe, (if you pleaſe) as it is almoſt for me to write theſe lines to you; it is not unknowne to your ſelfe what tranſcendent miſeries I ſuffered before this Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament by the Biſhops, &amp;c. for divers yeers together, and how that for betwixt eight and nine yeers I have in a manner conſtantly waited upon your Houſe for redreſſe, without any reall fruit at all to this day, though I dare ſafely ſay it, I have ſpent well nigh 1500.<abbr>l.</abbr> one way and another, ſince I firſt begun my ſuit unto you, divers hundreds of which I muſt in truth tell you I am at this time ingaged for, and owe at this houre, and how ſoon I may be throwne into a Jayle, and there rot for want of payment of it, and ſee my wife and tender babes periſh for want before my eyes, I know not; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore truly Sir, I muſt with bitterneſſe of ſpirit ſay, a happineſſe it had been for me, if when almoſt full eight years ago you voted me reparations to my barbarous ſufferings, you had voted me to everlaſting baniſhment, out of the land of my nativity, and that it ſhould have been immediate death for me to have returned, to have fought for any juſtice at your hands; for alas, Sir, what a happy man as to the world had I been? to have had the improvement of my waſted money, and my eight years hazardous ill ſpent time, in waiting upon you for your often promiſed Juſtice, in my calling in ſome forraigne land, for the ſubſiſtence of me and mine; whereas all the benefit I have really enjoyed from you hath been the tormenting of my ſpirits, and the filling of my bones with aches and paines, in thoſe hard, unrighteous and unjuſt impriſonments that I have ſix or ſeven ſeverall times ſuſtained from your Houſe, and their Committees, in which I will not now ſay your ſelfe had a conſiderable hand in ſome of them, and yet have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies been delivered by you as an innocent and righteous man, without ever having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing laid unto my charge: Sir, I have often had many faire promiſes from you, and ſo have ſome of my friends beſides of your readineſſe and deſirableneſſe to help me to juſtice and my own (though ſome other of my friends that have ſate within your walls have told me the quite contrary, which I have been loath to believe) and therefore I now write unto you, to put you to the teſt: Wherefore without any more delay I adjure you, <hi>as you will anſwer before God and his mighty Angells, that now you deale inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111285:19"/>
and honeſtly with me,</hi> and either help me effectually to get my Ordinance paſt your Houſe, <hi>for my</hi> 3000. <hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> reparations,</hi> and force that <hi>faith breaking</hi> man that hath not a ſpark of <hi>Gentleman</hi> in him, I mean Sir <hi>Charles Kemiſh,</hi> to help me to my 300. <abbr>l.</abbr> which by your aſſignment I ſhould have had four moneths ago from him, <hi>or els tell me plainly and truly you will not, cannot, or dare not (for feare of my adverſaries)</hi> med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with my buſineſſe to do me any effectuall good, and I do aſſure you I will take it for an honeſt finall anſwer, <hi>and never trouble you particularly any more,</hi> but put my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to a publike teſt, by one more printed addreſſe, ſutable to my extremities, and if I <hi>muſt periſh</hi> (becauſe I cannot, nor will not creaturize, to crouch unto mens corrupt luſts and wills) <hi>I periſh;</hi> but by Gods aſſiſtance I ſhall do the beſt I can, if it muſt needs be ſo, <hi>that it ſhall be with a witneſſe.</hi> So with my ſervice preſented unto you, being deſirous to wait upon you at your lodging for an anſwer, I reſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From my lodging in Brewers yard in Kings ſtreet Weſtminſter, <date>Decemb. 16. 1648.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Yours, very deſirous to have juſt cauſe to be Your Servant, <hi>John Lilburne.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>So when my Ordinance came to the Lords, they diſinabled me to cut down any more timber trees, then what was already fell'd, which I judged fitter for me to content my ſelf with, <hi>then to ſtruggle any longer to get it paſſe, as the Houſe of Commons had ſent it up,</hi> ſo, the Lords in two or three daies diſpatched it, and ſent it down to the Houſe of Commons for their concurrence, according to thoſe abridgements they had made in it, and taking my opportunity to ſpeak to thoſe in the Houſe of Commons, I had intereſt in, I intreated them to diſpute it no more, but paſſe it as the Lords had gelded it, and accordingly they did, the copy of which thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="ordinance">
                        <head>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Die Jovis</hi> 21. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1648.</date> An Ordinance of the <hi>Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament,</hi> for raiſing of <hi>three thouſand pounds</hi> out of the ſequeſtred <hi>estates and compoſitions</hi> of Sir <hi>Henry Gibb</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Henry Bellingham</hi> Knight and Baronet, and <hi>Thomas Bowes</hi> Eſquire, lying and being within the <hi>County of Durham,</hi> to be paid unto <hi>L. Col. John Lilburne,</hi> by the Committee of Sequeſtrations of the ſaid County, for and towards the reparation and damages of the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> which he ſuſtained by vertue &amp; colour of <hi>two unjuſt Sentences,</hi> or Decrees given and made againſt him in the late Court of Starchamber, <hi>the one the</hi> 13. <hi>of February</hi> 1637. <hi>the other the</hi> 18. <hi>of April</hi> 1638.</head>
                        <p>WHereas the cauſe of Lievt. Col. <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> concerning <hi>two ſentences</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt him in the late Court of <hi>Starchamber</hi> 13. February, <hi>decimo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Caroli Regis,</hi> and the 18. April <hi>decimo quarto Caroli Regis, (which were voted the</hi> 4. <hi>of May</hi> 1641. <hi>by the Houſe of Commons to be illegall, and againſt the liberty of the Subject, and alſo bloody, wicked, cruell, barbarous and tyrannicall)</hi> were tranſmitted from the ſaid Houſe of Commons unto the Houſe of <hi>Lords,</hi> in which the Houſe of <hi>Peers</hi> concurred in judgment, and the 13. of February 1645. <hi>declared the ſaid proceedings of the ſaid Starchamber againſt the ſaid</hi> John Lilburne <hi>to be illegall, moſt unjuſt, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the liberty of the Subject, and law of the land, and Magna Charta, and unfit to continue upon record, &amp;c.</hi> The ſaid <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> taking into their ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration the <hi>extraordinary ſufferings and barbarous tyranny</hi> that by colour of the ſaid <hi>unjuſt Decrees</hi> were inflicted upon the ſaid Lievt. Col. <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> and the long time hitherto <hi>elapſed</hi> without any ſatisfaction, do conceive it <hi>moſt juſt, equitable</hi> and <hi>reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> to repaire him in ſome conſiderable manner; and <hi>therefore</hi> in purſuance of <hi>two or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of the Houſe of Commons, <hi>one of the</hi> 22. <hi>of Auguſt</hi> 1648. <hi>and the other of the</hi>
                           <pb n="33" facs="tcp:111285:19"/>
5. <hi>of September</hi> 1648. have ordained, and be it hereby ordained by the <hi>Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parliament,</hi> and by the authority of the ſame, That the ſaid <hi>John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne</hi> ſhall have, <hi>and receive the ſum of</hi> 3000. <hi>
                              <abbr>l.</abbr> to be paid unto him or his Aſſignes by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Sequeſtrations for the County of Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham out of the firſt profits of the ſequeſtred eſtates both lands and goods of</hi> Sir Henry Gibb <hi>Knight,</hi>
                           <note n="*" place="margin">And therefore for the Committee of Durham, who by this Ordinance ſtand ingaged to pay me my <hi>3000.</hi> 
                              <abbr>l.</abbr> according to the tenure thereof, to ſuffer <hi>Sir Arthur Haſlerig</hi> [that is no member of their Committee, and ſo by conſequence hath no more to doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them then any other man] by his meer will juſt tyrant like to take my money.</note> Sir Henry Bellingham <hi>Knight and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet, and</hi> Thomas Bowes <hi>Eſquire, lying and being in the County of Durham,</hi> having been all <hi>active</hi> in the late Northern inſurrections, and <hi>aiding</hi> and <hi>aſſiſting</hi> to the moſt wicked invaſion of <hi>Duke Hamilton.</hi> And the ſaid Committee are hereby authoriſed to ſell all ſuch <hi>woods</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept timber trees now ſtanding) as may conveniently be ſpared, and now ſtanding upon the ſaid lands <hi>(or already felled)</hi> or any of them. <hi>And if the ſaid</hi> Sir Henry Gibb, Sir Henry Bellingham, <hi>and</hi> Thomas Bowes, <hi>or any of them ſhall compound for their eſtate, ſo much of the ſaid three thouſand pounds as then ſhall remain unſatisfied, ſhall be paid unto the ſaid</hi> John Lilburne, or his aſſignes, out of their, <hi>or the first of their Compoſitions.</hi> And this Ordinance or copie thereof atteſted under the hand, or hands of the Clerk, or <hi>Clerks of one or both Houſes of Parliament,</hi> ſhall be a ſufficient Warrant to the ſaid <hi>Committee</hi> of Sequeſtrations in the ſaid <hi>County of Durham,</hi> to pay the ſaid 3000.<abbr>l.</abbr> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s before expreſſed, unto the ſaid <hi>John Lilburne</hi> or his aſſignes; and likewiſe to indemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ifie and ſave harmleſſe, all, and every perſon or perſons that ſhall any way act in the performance of the true intent and meaning of this Ordinance.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Joh. Brown Cler. Parliamentorum. H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>With which Ordinance I poſted away to you of the Committee of Durham, where as you may remember, I found Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> amongſt you, continually ſitting with you, not onely as a Member of your Committee of <hi>Militia,</hi> and of <hi>Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> but alſo Chair-man to them both; and not only that, <hi>but alſo Lord paramount over you all, doing even what himſelfe pleaſed by meere will, tearing your Orders, raſing, cancelling, and putting in what he pleaſed;</hi> of the moſt of which I then being an eye-witneſſe, I very ſeriouſly (as you may well remember) inquired of my <hi>Father,</hi> Colonell <hi>Midford,</hi> M. <hi>Bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and your ſelfe, whether by Ordinance of Parliament Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> was a Member of your Committees? and you all told me no, he was not of either of them; at which I wondered, and ſtood amazed, that he durſt do that which he conſtantly did, and that you were men of ſuch low and <hi>meane ſpirits, as to ſuffer him, yea, or to permit him ſo much as to ſit amongſt you;</hi> but it was replyed to me, as you may remember, how could you help it? for your County was more in ſlavery then all the Counties of England, <hi>never having either Knights, or Burgeſſes in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſpeak and act there for the welfare of your County, or any that belong to it, and wiſh'd it well,</hi> and beſides, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> was a great and a powerfull man both in Parliament and Army, and had ſouldiers enough at his heels: upon all which he bears himſelfe ſo high, that he preſumes to do even what he pleaſeth, and who dare to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule him? <hi>for, hath he not meerly by his will, and of his own Authority laid foure ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a chaldern</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> very excize of coles alone in the two Ports of Newcaſtle and Sunderland, being commonly by the knowingeſt Ship-maſters, &amp;c. computed to be worth wel nigh a hundred thouſand pounds per annum.</note> 
               <hi>Excize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on coles?</hi> (which at the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111285:20"/>
with you are ſold under twenty ſhillings the chaldern) <hi>in which arbitrary taxation not onely all London is concerned, but almoſt all the Sea and great Townes in the South of England, &amp;c. and yet the City of London it ſelfe never proſecuted him therfore, no nor ſo much as complained of him,</hi> and therefore much more may he doe what he pleaſeth amongſt you, who rationally have ſcarce any means afforded you ſo much as to complaine of him, much leſſe to help your ſelves aganſt him, and therefore you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed me then to heare, and ſee, and ſay nothing, but look after my owne buſineſſe, to get that diſpatched, which you very well know I fully acquainted your Committee with at Durham, while Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig was there,</hi> before whom my Ordinance was read, and approved of without the leaſt exceptions, and the originalls delivered to your Clerke to record in your Journall, and with whoſe conſent and approbation (I meane Sir <hi>Arthur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) your Committee made this following Order.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>Dunelm. <date>
                                 <hi>Septimo die Januarii,</hi> 1648.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>WHereas by an Ordinance of Parliament dated Decemb. 21. 1648. it is declared, <hi>That Lievtenant Col</hi> John Lilburne <hi>having had two Sentences pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in the late Court of Starchamber, Febr.</hi> 13. decimo tertio Caroli Regis, <hi>and</hi> 18. <hi>of April,</hi> decimo quarto Caroli Regis, <hi>which were voted the</hi> 4. <hi>of May,</hi> 1641. <hi>by the Houſe of Commons to be illegall, and againſt the Liberty of the Subject, and alſo bloody, wicked, cruell, barbarous and tyrannicall,</hi> were tranſmitted from the ſaid Houſe of Commons unto the Houſe of Lords; in which the Houſe of Peers concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in judgement, and the 13. of Febr. 1645. <hi>declared the proceedings of the ſaid Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber to be illegall, and moſt unjuſt, and against the Liberty of the Subject, and the Law of the Land, and Magna Charta, and unfit to continue upon record, &amp;c.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> did conceive it moſt juſt, equitable and reaſonable, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire him in ſome conſiderable manner; <hi>and therefore ordained, that the ſaid Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-Col.</hi> John Lilburn <hi>ſhall have and receive the ſum of</hi> 3000.<abbr>l.</abbr> 
                           <hi>to be paid unto him, or his Aſſigns, by the Committee of Sequeſtrations for the County of Durham, out of the firſt profits of the ſequeſtred eſtates, both lands and goods of Sir</hi> Henry Gibbs <hi>Knight, Sir</hi> Henry Bellingham, <hi>Knight and Baronet, and</hi> Thomas Bowes <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, lying and being within this County of Durham, having been all active in the late Northern Inſurrections, and aiding and aſſisting to the moſt wicked invaſion of Duke</hi> Hambleton, in obedience unto which ſaid Ordinance, it is this day ordered by the Committee of Sequeſtrations for this County, <hi>That the ſaid Lievtenant Colonell</hi> Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn <hi>or his aſſigns, ſhall and may, and hereby is authorized to go to the ſeverall Tenants and Creditors of the ſaid ſeverall Delinquents, to demand and receive the ſeverall rents, profits and debts, due to each or any of them, for and towards the payment of the ſaid three thouſand pounds,</hi> and his or their receipt ſhall be their ſufficient diſcharge, and the ſaid Tenants, Farmers, or Creditors, are preſently, or within 14. daies after, to ſend copies of the ſaid receipts, to this Committee; <hi>and the ſaid Lievtenant Colonell</hi> John Lilburn, <hi>is from time to time to certifie this Committee, the manner of his proceedings herein,</hi> and he is alſo authorized hereby, to go and repair to <hi>Henry Young, Banchman of the Collyery of Carterthorn,</hi> or to his Deputy or Deputies, and fully to enquire and inform himſelf of the true eſtate and value of the ſaid <hi>Collyery,</hi> as relating to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Thomas Bowes;</hi> As alſo to repair to the <hi>Iron Mill and Furnace at Hunwick and Witton,</hi> and there to take a true and perfect <hi>account,</hi> and <hi>Inventory,</hi> of all the <hi>Stock, Implements, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſills,</hi> and <hi>neceſſaries,</hi> and of all profits and advantages ariſing, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or coming thereby, unto the ſaid Mr. <hi>Thomas Bowes,</hi> and ſpeedily to certifie this Committee thereof, alſo to ſummon, <hi>John Hodgſon Steward of the Iron works at Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
                           <pb n="35" facs="tcp:111285:20"/>
and the ſaid <hi>Henry Young,</hi> to be before this Committee at <hi>Gatſhead,</hi> upon <hi>Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day next,</hi> to give in and teſtifie their knowledge, touching Mr. <hi>Bowes his interest,</hi> in the ſaid Iron works and Collyery.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Iſaac Gilpin Cler. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>By vertue of which Order, my Father and my ſelf went to the Tenants of the three forementioned Delinquents, as alſo to the foreſaid <hi>Young</hi> and <hi>Hodgſon,</hi> which <hi>Young</hi> and <hi>Hudgſon</hi> according to the aforeſaid order appeared at Gateſide before Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Haſlerig,</hi> and your ſaid Committee of Sequeſtrations unto whom I punctually gave an ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct account of Mr. <hi>Bowes his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oles</hi> at <hi>Karterthorn,</hi> and his Iron Mill and <hi>Forge at Hunwick and Witton,</hi> upon which the foreſaid Stewards were examined what they conceived M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Bowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> intereſt in the ſaid Colepits and Iron Mill to be worth, and after they had given in their Verdict and opinion, the ſaid Committee of Sequeſtration ſold (with my good liking) the ſaid <hi>Bowes</hi> his intereſt to Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> for 400. <abbr>l</abbr> preſent money, upon his ingagement to pay it me at London, (which he did) within the compaſſe of about a moneth after, as part of my 3000. <abbr>l.</abbr> and I alſo received then in the Countrey of the reſpective Tenants &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. of the foreſaid three Gentlemen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt 100. and 200. <abbr>l.</abbr> ready money, all which I certified your Committee of at Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, and by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeciall order, delivered to their <hi>Clark</hi> and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>itor copies of all the diſcharges I had given the ſeverall Tenants, who comparing them with the reſpective rentalls and <hi>deductions for aſſeſſements and free-quarter</hi> (the originalls of which they had by them) did audit my accounts, and gave me a diſcharge under b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hands upon the eighth day of <hi>February,</hi> 1648. ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned <hi>Iſaac Gilpin Cler. Com Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> per Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t Haw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Auditor, ſo that now I have from ſtep to ſtep ſhewed you my right and ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to my 3000. <abbr>l.</abbr> which is not ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gratuity given me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as ſome men ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine by the Parliament, but the iſſue and product of ſeverall legall Parliamentary judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>judicially given me for damage ſuſtained in body, eſtate,</hi> and loſſe of time and trade, by illegall unjuſt decrees made and given againſt me, which Parliamentary judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and decrees of mine, <hi>and ſome of them of eight years ſtanding, before any warrs or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> betwixt the King and Parliament, others of</hi> 5 <hi>and</hi> 4. <hi>years ſtanding, while the Lords and Commons were a free, juſt and unqueſtionable Parliament, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> opinion of all the Parliamenteers in England, others of my decrees and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments meerly in confirmations of the former, of</hi> 3. <hi>and</hi> 2. <hi>years ſtanding, while <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th Houſes were commonly received and owned for an unforc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, unpurged, and unraviſhed Parliament;</hi> and the very laſt paſſing of my Ordinance was, by both Houſes before the Lords diſſolution, or the Kings beheading, whoſe death in Law unqueſtionably put a period to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>In moſt of which judgements,<note place="margin">For full pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe of which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, read my arguments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſecond edition of my book of the <hi>8.</hi> of <hi>June 1649.</hi> in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, The legall F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill Liberties of the people of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land revived, <hi>pag. 55. 56 57.</hi> and Mr. <hi>William P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ins</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in his late book, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the illegall tax of <hi>90.</hi> thouſand pounds per annum. <hi>pag. 3. 46 47.</hi>
               </note> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig was one of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udges,</hi> I am ſure of it eminently in ſome of them, and who was one of thoſe that was active in putting me into a quiet, juſt, and legall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion (for ſo it was eminently up in his own princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) of my long ſtrugled for, and dear bought right, <hi>unto which in the ſtricteſt eye of God or man,</hi> I have as true a judiciall legall right unto, as either he or you have, or ever had, to any cloaths you wore in your lives, and therefore Sir I may well call it theft in him, <hi>in ſtealing my goods or moneys from me by will and force, just like a cutter upon the high way,</hi> yea and by his own and the late Parliaments principles, <hi>treaſon it ſelf,</hi> in diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſeſſing me of my le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall and juſt come by eſtate, without any manner <hi>of proceedings is Law; yea or ſo
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111285:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:111285:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:111285:22"/>
much as upon any proceedings upon a paper Petition, or ſo much as ever ſummoning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to anſwer for my ſelf,</hi> or to know what he had to lay to my charge, as a colourable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to take it away from me: it is impoſſible for him to plead ignorance of my right, he having as is before truly declared, been privy to all the circumſtances of my juſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, yea as I underſtand, my Father did not a little plead my right with him, and produced my Ordinance &amp;c. to his face to maintain it, when he took it away, which notwithſtanding he valued not, <hi>but moſt maliciouſly, premiditately, and in deſpite and contempt of the Law of England, and moſt trayterouſly in ſubverſion thereof, hath exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed an arbitrary and tyrannicall power over and above the Law,</hi> in his taking it away, for which felonious and trayte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous Action of his, by Gods aſſiſtance I will ſtick as cloſe to him, as ever his ſhirt did to his back, or as ever I did to the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who for leſſe villanies then his, I ſaw loſe his head as a Traytor upon Tower Hill.</p>
            <p>Sir, the late King hath loſt his head by Sir <hi>Arthur and his aſſociates for tyranny,</hi> in advancing his will above the Law of England, as in his impeachment, printed at the laſt end of my late Impeachment of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> you may read <hi>pag.</hi> 57. 58. And yet I am ſure he formerly, and (for any thing I groundedly know to the contrary) legally impeached <hi>Haſlerig of high Treaſon,</hi> and yet never pretended any right to a penny of his eſtate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conviction, but <hi>Haſlerig</hi> nor any body elſe never laid any crime in the world to my charge, either of Treaſon particularly, or of Felony, or Miſdemeanour, or any thing elſe, and yet hath ſeized upon my eſtate, without any pretence or ſhadow, or colour of Law.</p>
            <p>And that the King impeached him, you may read in 1. part Parliament. book Decla. <hi>pag.</hi> 34. 35. which <hi>verbatim</hi> thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="indictment">
                        <head>Articles of high Treaſon, and other Miſdemeanours againſt the Lord <hi>Kimbolton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pym, John Hampden, Denzill Hollis,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> and <hi>William Strode,</hi> being all Members of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>That they have trayterouſly</hi> endeavoured to ſubvert the fundamentall Laws and Government of this Kingdome, and deprive the King of his legall power, and to <hi>place on Subjects,</hi> an arbitrary and tyrannicall power.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>That they</hi> have endeavoured by many foul aſperſions, upon his Majeſty <hi>and his Government,</hi> to alienate the affections of his people, and to make his Majeſty <hi>odious to them.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. <hi>That they</hi> have endeavoured to draw his Majeſties late Army to diſobedience <hi>to his Majeſties command,</hi> and to ſide with them in their trayterous deſign.</item>
                           <item>4. <hi>That they</hi> have trayterouſly invited and incouraged a Forraign Power, <hi>to invade</hi> his Majeſties Kingdome of England.</item>
                           <item>5. <hi>That they</hi> have trayterouſly endeavoured to ſubvert the very rights and beings of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>6. <hi>That for</hi> the compleating of their trayterous deſignes, they have endeavoured as far as in them lay, by force and terrour, to compell the Parliament <hi>to joyn with</hi> them in their trayterous deſigns, and to that end, have <hi>actually raiſed,</hi> and countenanced tumults againſt the King and Parliament.</item>
                           <item>7. <hi>That they</hi> have trayterouſly conſpired to levy, and actually have levied <hi>warr</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:111285:22"/>And therefore the premiſſes duly conſidered, <hi>Haſlerig</hi> hath dealt more unjuſtly, more illegal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and more unrighteouſly with me, then ever the King dealt with him, or his Aſſociates, and therefore as a Tyrant and a Traitour he ought to die therefore upon his own practiſed and declared principles. But moreover, although the King formally and for any thing I know to the contrary, Parliamentarily impeached him as a Traitour, and yet for all that never ſought for or challenged any of his money, Lands, or Goods, untill he were Legally convicted: and yet by the Parliament it ſelf it was looked upon for ſuch a violation of the Law (becauſe it was not as they pretended formall in every punctilio according to the Law) <hi>as occaſioned the higheſt Declarations againſt the King that their pens</hi> could invent, with aggravation upon aggravation, and no perſonall recantatation from the King himſelf could ſerve their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rn (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he illuſtration of which you may notably and fully read in the 2 Edition of my book of the 8 of June 1649 pag. 12. 13. 14. 15. 18. 19. 20. 21. 'till they had made it the firſt declared occaſion to ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dle the flames of all the 'late eight yeers cruell warres in <hi>England:</hi> yea and for it, and ſuch like as it, at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion they took off the Kings head as a Tyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, 'for that he had ſet his will above the law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y which he ought to have governed, as appears in the firſt Article of his impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Therefore let <hi>Haſlerig</hi> look to himſelf; for I do b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leeve if he or hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bloodthirſty aſſociates ſhould murder me, yet God out of my aſhes, would raiſe up ſome vigorouſly to endeavour to bring h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s neck to the gallows, or his head to the block for his Tyrannies and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bitrary dealing with me, and for my part ſo long as I have bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th (by the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aſſiſtance of God) I ſhall not bate him an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce although I periſh in the proſecution of him, let him and all his aſſociates do the worſt they dare or can.</p>
            <p>And therefore Sir, I moſt earneſtly beg of you, to intreat my Father to pluck up ſo much courage, as truly and exactly to ſtate the preſent condition of my bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe with <hi>Haſlerig,</hi> and ſend me an exact Narrative of it from the beginning of <hi>Haſlerigs medling with it:</hi> and alſo I intreat you your ſelf, to certifie me (if you dare) under your hand, the manner and particulars of all his arbitrary dealings with your particular ſelf, and your Committees &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">And whether that he himſelf were not the abſolute and ſingle Inſtrument, that cauſed you and my Father for your publike and known good affection to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth and nothing elſe, to be turned out of the Commiſſion of the Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And when he had ſo done, whether he alone by his meer Will and Prerogative did not name Maſter <hi>Henry Draper,</hi> and cauſed him to be made a Juſtice of the Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> although as I am credibly and certainly informed, he was a notable Cavalier, and had a Commiſſion from the Earle of Newcaſtle, and not three months before HA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SLERIGS making him a Juſtice of Peace, he had paid part of his Compoſition to HASLERIGS own particular hands or his Treaſurer by his order and appointment</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whether he did not alſo lately name, and by his Prerogative will put in Sir <hi>Richard B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> for another Juſtice of Peace for your County, who to my own knowledge was about my laſt being in your County found and proved a Delinquent; Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being one of his chiefeſt Proſecutors, and ſtands ſequeſtred as a Delinquent Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier to this day?</p>
            <p>And whether he did not lately the ſame to Sir <hi>George Vane,</hi> who you may remember at the Committee betwixt you and <hi>John Blaſton,</hi> and his Cavalier brother in Law, Mr. <hi>Shadforth,</hi> where Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> (at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in <hi>Febr.</hi> laſt) ſate Chairman? I offered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> face, and all the reſt of his fellow Members to prove Sir <hi>Georg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Vane</hi> a Cavalier; and to have been actually in Arms with the King at <hi>Edge hill</hi> and alſo ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>Haſlerigs</hi> face, and the whole Committees, <hi>Haſlerigs baſe and partiall dealings in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111285:23"/>
the North,</hi> in contradicting the Orders of your Committe of Sequeſtration, and racing out of their Orders what he pleaſed in the caſe of <hi>Shadforth</hi> and your ſelf, and putting in what he pleaſed, yea and againſt the Order and mind of the Committee would have i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in his pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ticular Order to paſſe for your and <hi>Shadforths</hi> drawing ſtakes (to the great intentionall cheating and cozening of the Common wealth, after <hi>Shadforth</hi> was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved a Delinquent upon the 14. Articles, and to ſave himſelf had impeached you (who deſired nothing but a fair and judiciall triall) to be another; of which falſe Charge, ſince as I underſtand, for all <hi>Haſlerigs</hi> and <hi>John Blaſtons</hi> power and malice; The preſent Jancto hath fully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you, which <hi>Shadforth</hi> by his meere will as I underſtand he hath ſince made a juſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of peace &amp;c. as alſo Colonell <hi>Francis Wren:</hi> who he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf knowes, was moſt baſely and vildly, in the head of his Regiment in <hi>Scotland,</hi> caſhie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by his friend <hi>Cromwell</hi> for a deſperate plunderer &amp;c. And all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s he hath done as to me clearly appears, <hi>that he may rule and govern you by his will and pleaſure, and have none in power that ſhall dare to controul him, or to tell tales of him:</hi> of which rather then he will faile, hee will againſt his owne declared Principles, and the 'Ordinances of Lords and Commons, yea the acts of the preſent Juncto make uſe of the notableſt Cavaliers amongſt you to be your principall governours, and more eſpeciall Rulers and <hi>yet lately would have hanged me for but appearing correſponding with the Princes Agents, of wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch he was ſo zealous to take away my life for that rather then he would fail, he &amp;c. attempted to bribe and hire falſe witneſſe to ſwear againſt me: declaring bare correſpondency with the Prince his Agents to be crime enough to take away my life,</hi> as is truly noted and declared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pag. 7. 8. 9. 10. 'O brave Arthur; whom for his baſe and villanous wicked deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with me &amp;c. I hope not onely to ſcare but alſo really to ſcourge, and thereby put him into a greater fright, then he was in when the Earle of <hi>Stamford</hi> (a leſſer man then himſelf) tamed him as he was going to his houſe nigh <hi>Iſlington,</hi> although he had his ſword by his ſide; of which a few days after like a poor cowardly School boy, with little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his finger in his eye, he complained of to his Maſters or Aſſociates in the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>And as for your deſire in your letter, for me a few dayes to come downe, to look after my owne buſineſſe my ſelfe.: I cannot but return you this anſwer. Firſt, If I would I cannot, for I am not abſolutely at liberty as you ſuppoſe, onely I have liberty upon the day time to go ſee my diſtreſſed wife and family, which I procured not upon a petition to the houſe '(as their Friday Newes-monger <hi>Henry Walker</hi> that lying and baſe fellow with other falſhoods about me hath lately printed) but upon a letter the Copy of which thus followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>For my honoured and noble friends, the Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of Groby, Colonel <hi>Henry Martin,</hi> Col. <hi>Francis Ruſſell,</hi> Capt. <hi>Fry</hi> or any of them theſe preſent.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord and Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="margQuotes">A Greater triall then ever I had upon me in my life, <hi>forces and compells</hi> me to bee troubleſome unto you, or elſe I ſhould not have preſumed to have put you upon ſo unwelcome an imployment as to make a publike Motion for a man ſo deſpicable and obnoxious to the eyes of the great men in preſent power as I am; but neceſſity hath no Law, and therefore I muſt acquaint you, that the over-ruling diſpoſing hand of him (that without whoſe over-ruling providence, the meaneſt hair of my head ſhall not fall to the ground) hath ſo pleaſed to lay his viſiting hand upon my eldeſt ſon by a violent ſicknes for this 3. weeks, and my ſelfe being very dear to the poor boy conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111285:23"/>
in his ſicknes to the exceeding ſpending of his ſpirits) CRYED OUT TO SEE HIS FATHER OR BEE CARRIED TO PRISON TO HIM, and upon Saturday was ſevennight, my child being very ill all night, crying ſcores and ſome hundreds of times for his Father to come to him, the knowledge of which in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning very much pierced the <hi>bowels</hi> of his tender mother, and ſuppoſing that if I could be got to come and ſee him, it might much refreſh his ſpirits, and ſo eaſe the child of ſome of his extremitie of pain; Upon Lords day after in the morning in little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then half a <hi>diſtempered condition,</hi> ſhe poſted away to Mr. <hi>Holland</hi> to <hi>Sommerſet houſe,</hi> and with teares begged him to get me two or three daies liberty upon my Paroll to come and ſee him, knowing he had if he pleaſed power enough to get it done, and have ſince again and again ſent to him, but all in vain; Truly Gentlemen I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten muſed upon that ſaying of the Spirit of God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.10. <hi>That the tender mercies of the wicked are cruelty;</hi> but that the tender mercies of men profeſſing God, godlineſſe and a publike Reformation of tyranny and cruelty, ſhould be ſo full of Barbariſme, as to TORMENT THE POOR CHILD, FOR THEIR INDIGNATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON AGAINST ME HIS FATHER, is that that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> and amazeth me, and makes death more deſirable to me (fully knowing in whom I do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> beleeve) then to live under ſuch mens Government. Sure I am the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>SHOPS in the days of the higheſt of <hi>Lands</hi> Tyranny, had more bowels of compaſſion in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>em to men in my caſe, as I could inſtance; and all my torments ſuffered by then I can never equall to this. But how-ever, I muſt be patient, although my poor B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in the height of torment till this afternoon, with HIS ABSENT FATHER CONTINUALLY IN HIS MOUTH, ſo long as he had ſtrength to ſpeak of me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> whoſe ſorrows and miſeries, with both my other childrens falling ſick upon Sunday <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſt, of the ſmall Pocks (the youngeſt of which ſucks its mothers breſts) hath ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed her ſpirits, that yeſter-night it brought her cloſe to deaths doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>; Of which, when I underſtood to day, I poſted away to you four, to BEG AND BESEECH YOU, or any one of you, at this great ſtrait, to make a Motion openly in your Houſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> little liberty for me to go ſee my diſtreſſed Wife and Children. I CONFESSE I SHOULD NOT HAVE PUT YOU TO SUCH A TROUBLE FOR THE SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VING OF MY OVVN PARTICULAR LIFE; But your Houſe being riſen, the meſſenger brings me tidings of the death of my poor babe, and the exceeding i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lneſſe of my Wife, and her exceeding deſire to ſee me in her great diſtreſſe. Therefore I earneſtly beſeech you, as bowels of men dwell within you, to make an effectuall and ſpeedy Motion in your open Houſe, for a few dayes liberty for me to go ſee my diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Wife, giving ſatisfactory Security to the Lieutenant of the Tower for my faithfull return at the hour appointed. Make your own terms as ſtrict as you pleaſe; FOR THOUGH I LIE IN A DUNGEON IN FETTERS OF IRON AT MY COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING BACK, I care not, ſo I may but ſee her. So, with my reall Service preſented to you all four, craving your pardon for my troubling of you for a Motion in your Houſe, which I know cannot be pleaſing to you, I take leave to reſt,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From my cloſe Impriſonment in the Tower of London, <date>this 17 of July, 1649.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>SIRS,</salute>
                     <signed>Your affectionate and hearty Friend and Servant, <hi>JOHN LILBURN.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:111285:24"/>Upon the delivery of which ſaid Letter to Col. <hi>Henry Martin,</hi> (the other three which it was directed to, being out of Town) he procured this following Order.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Mercurii 18. July 1649.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that the Lieutenant of the Tower of London, permit <hi>Lieut. Col. JOHN LILBURN to go out of the Tower,</hi> to viſit his Wife and Children, being ſick, upon ſuch ſecurity (as the Lieutenant of the Tower ſhall think fit) to render himſelf again to the priſon of the Tower.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>HENRY SCOBEL, Cler. Parliament.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Secondly, Being as I am, although my not coming down would loſe me ſix times as much as <hi>Haſlerig</hi> hath a ready ſeiſed upon; yet could I not be free in my own ſpirit (againſt the dictates of which I will not go for all the world) to addreſſe my ſelf to thoſe men for liberty to come down; no, nor ſo much as give my conſent that any other ſhall do it for me.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, If I were abſolutely at liberty, I ſhould ſcarce judge it either wiſdom or diſcretion, to come immediately under the armed power of a man that hath ſo thirſted after my blood, <hi>and dealt ſo illegally and barbarouſly with me as</hi> Haſlerig <hi>hath done,</hi> in the face of the throng of my friends: and without all queſtion he that at London (where I have more friends then <hi>Haſlerig</hi> himſelf) will not ſtick to run the hazards of going ſo many indirect wayes to work, to take away my <hi>innocent life,</hi> will make no bones (himſelf) to knock my brains out, could he catch me in the remote clutches of his armed mercenary power at New-caſtle, far off from the throng of my friends. So with my true and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged love and reſpect preſented to your ſelf, and my Ant your ſecond ſelf, I heartily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you to God, and reſt:</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Impriſonment in the Tower of London, <date>this 18 of Aug. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your faithfull and affectionate loving Nephew, <hi>JOHN LILBURN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
